<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the interest of the princes and states of Christendome. Written in French by the most noble and illustrious Prince, the Duke of Rohan. Translated into English by H.H.</title>
            <title>De l'interest des princes. English</title>
            <author>Rohan, Henri, duc de, 1579-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119221</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854428</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 936:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the interest of the princes and states of Christendome. Written in French by the most noble and illustrious Prince, the Duke of Rohan. Translated into English by H.H.</title>
                  <title>De l'interest des princes. English</title>
                  <author>Rohan, Henri, duc de, 1579-1638.</author>
                  <author>Hunt, Henry, 17th/18th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 127, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Imprimatur. Tho. Broun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Prid. Id. Jul.] M. DC. XXXX. [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Henry Hunt, of: Rohan, Henri.  De l'interest des princes.</note>
                  <note>The dedication, pi2 (signed "Henr. Hunt") was printed in London.--STC.</note>
                  <note>imprimatur on separate leaf bound before title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sovereignty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  Politics and government --  1517-1648.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:19849:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur. Prid. Id. Jul. M.DC.XL.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Broun.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19849:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE INTEREST OF THE PRINCES AND STATES OF CHRISTENDOME.</p>
            <p>Written in French by the moſt noble and illuſtrious Prince, the Duke of Rohan.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Translated into English By H. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at Paris.</p>
            <p>M.DC.XXXX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19849:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19849:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, JOHN LORD FINCHE, BARON OF FORDWICH, Lord Keeper of the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and one of his Majeſties moſt honorable Privie Councell, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His little Booke being written by ſo excellent a perſon as the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> and treating of ſo weighty a Subject as the <hi>Intereſt of the Princes and States of Chriſtendome,</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived alſo with good eſteeme by ſome judicious men, I thought it not amiſſe to communicate the ſame, imploying the advantage of ſo many ſpare minutes (during my abode in <hi>France</hi>) as to make it ſpeake <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Then being invited to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to the light, to the publike view, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like voyce taught it to implore your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> protection, whether be conſidered the <hi>quality</hi> of the Author, the <hi>gravity</hi> of the Matter, or
<pb facs="tcp:19849:3"/>
               <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the Originall wherein it was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For as the Author was noble, and eminent in his place; in like manner is your Honour, ſhining in your orb as a ſtarre of the firſt Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, lending a moſt benigne and gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to the just cauſes of the oppreſſed, diſtreſſed, fatherleſſe, and widow. The Matter is of politick maximes, and divers remarkable occurrences in ſundry Republikes: and to whom now can this be more aptly addreſſed then to a principall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of State, in whom Prudence, Science, and Integrity (in a ſweet harmony) doe all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to make a perfect conduct of affaires, for the glory of God, the honour of the King, and the good of this Church and Common-wealth? Laſtly, the Originall from whence it was derived, being <hi>French:</hi> your admired knowledge, and unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell'd expreſsions in the ſame language, may ſpeake you as well a <hi>patterne</hi> in the originall, as a <hi>Patron</hi> in this tranſlation. For my owne part (if it may be permitted to ſay any thing of my ſelfe) I ſpeak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently <hi>(My Lord)</hi> with your permiſsion, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I had not ſo much vanity as to perſwade my ſelfe that any thing could proceed from me, worthy your reception, or advantagious to your Honour,
<pb facs="tcp:19849:3"/>
(ſince that my act herein ſhewed more of duty then merit, and its inſufficiencie demanded rather par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don then remuneration;) yet had I ſome kinde of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that a favourable acceptation would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine what I most humbly preſent, ſeeing the moſt heroick minde diſdaines not the meaneſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, but like the Sunne (that nobler Planet) ſpreads his indifferent rayes upon all, as well on ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as glorious objects. Theſe and ſuch like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations made me adventure (but with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and humility) to prefix here your moſt Honorable Name, that thereby this Book might live; and withall inceſſantly beſeeching him whoſe name is <hi>I AM,</hi> to preſerve and continue Yours in perpetuall <hi>being,</hi> in all honour and prosperity, and to <hi>write</hi> your <hi>name</hi> in a larger volume, <hi>the Book of life.</hi> For which end the <hi>Lord</hi> be ſtill your <hi>Keeper,</hi> and <hi>Seale you with</hi> that great <hi>Seale, the holy Spirit of promiſe, to the day of redemption.</hi> So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humbly devoted HENR. HUNT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19849:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19849:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS <hi>OF</hi> THE INTEREST OF THE Princes and States of Chriſtendome.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He preface pag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of Spaine pag. <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of France p. <hi>13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of the Princes of Italie. pag. <hi>18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of the ſea of Rome. p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of the Duke of Sauoy. pag. <hi>24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of Germanie p. <hi>26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of the Suiſſes and of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prouinces of the Low-Countries p. <hi>31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the intereſt of England. p. <hi>34.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:19849:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE SECOND PART</hi> OF The intereſt of the Princes and States of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, the Preface. p. <hi>38.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt diſcourſe vpon the affaire of the League. p. <hi>40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Second diſcourſe vpon the warre of Sauoy. p. <hi>58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Third diſcourſe vpon the difference that happened betvveen Pope Paul V. and the Republike of Venice, the yeare <hi>1605.</hi> p. <hi>64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fourth diſcourſe concerning the Truce of the Low-Countries with the King of Spaine pag. <hi>81.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fifth diſcourſe vpon the affaire about the ſucceſsion of Cleues and Iulliers. p. <hi>93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſixt diſcourſe vpon the Election of the Count Palatine to the Kingdome of Bohemia. pag. <hi>103.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Seuenth deſcourſe vpon the commotions that happened in Italie, for the ſucceſsion of the Dutchies of Mantua and Montferrat. p. <hi>117.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19849:5"/>
            <head>OF THE INTEREST, OF THE PRINCES AND STATES OF CHRISTEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE PRINCES commaund the <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>Intereſt</hi> commaunds The <hi>Princes.</hi> The knowledge of this <hi>Intereſt</hi> is as much more raiſed aboue that of <hi>Princes</hi> actions, as they themſelues are aboue the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> The <hi>Prince</hi> may deceiue himſelfe, his <hi>Counſell</hi> may be corrupted, but the intereſt alone can neuer faile. According as it is well or ill vnderſtood, it maketh <hi>States</hi> to liue or die. And as it allwaies aimeth at the <hi>augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> or at leaſtwiſe the <hi>conſeruation</hi> of a <hi>State,</hi> ſo likewiſe to get thither, it ought to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19849:6"/>
varie according to the times. So that to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well the intereſt of the Princes of this time, wee need not remount very high, but onely take the ſtanding of the preſent affaires. For this purpoſe one ought to lay for a ground, that there be two Powers in <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which are as the two <hi>Poles,</hi> from when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce deſcend the influences of peace and warre vpon the other ſtates, to wit, the howſes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> This of <hi>Spaine</hi> finding it ſelfe augmented all at once, hath not beene able to conceale the deſigne shee had to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke her ſelfe <hi>Miſtreſſe,</hi> and cauſe the <hi>Sunne</hi> of a new <hi>Monarchie</hi> to riſe in the <hi>Weſt.</hi> That of <hi>France</hi> is forthwith carried to make a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſe. The other <hi>Princes</hi> are annexed to the one, or the other, according to their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> But forſomuch as this <hi>intereſt</hi> (as it hath beene well or ill followed) hath cauſed the ruine of ſome, or the greatneſſe of others, I haue purpoſed to publish in this preſent Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiſe. Firſt what was the true intereſt of theſe two mightie Powers, and then of the other which ſeeme in ſome manner to depend on their protection. Next of all I shall shew how
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19849:6"/>
much has beene the digreſſion from this true intereſt, either becauſe the <hi>Prince</hi> hath not well vnderſtood it, or elſe for that he was diſguiſed by the corruption of his <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19849:7"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST, OF SPAINE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>PAINE</hi> is at the head of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> where the <hi>Ocean</hi> ſerues her for bounds, vpon the entrance of the <hi>Mediterranean ſea,</hi> which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates the ſame from <hi>Affricke,</hi> hauing the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> mountaines for barriers againſt <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</hi> On this great Country ſo well ſituated, do depend many <hi>States</hi> ſpread in diuerſe parts of the world. <hi>Philip</hi> King of Spaine who attempted to extend this vaſt power to the top of all greatneſse (finding himſelfe leſse ſitt for warre then <hi>ciuill buſineſses</hi>) judged that <hi>Monarchies</hi> got as it were in poſt, by the valour of warlike <hi>Princes,</hi> are not of like continuance as thoſe which they get by eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishingh a good <hi>Counſell,</hi> and which are founded vpon good <hi>maximes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19849:7"/>Becauſe that theſe great <hi>Conquerrours,</hi> (who thinke onely of vanquishing, and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their dominions, and not of founding Lawes for their ſubſiſtence) being not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſucceeded by ſuch as equall their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and the vanquished people hauing not yet loſt the memorie of their libertie, or of their auncient <hi>Lords,</hi> are eaſily carried to any change, ſeeing themſelues deliuered from the feare of him that had ſubjected them, Which made this wiſe <hi>Prince</hi> reſolue to follow his owne diſpoſition, and chooſe a courſe moſt agreeable to his impenetrable humour, that is, to proſecute his deſignes vnder a profound diſſimulation.</p>
               <p>To this end, he fixed the ſeat of his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in <hi>Spaine,</hi> that he might from thence conueigh warmth to the members looſened from this body, and might with more eaſe (conſeruing peace by his preſence) trouble all the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> by his ſubtilties. But the time fayling him to accomplish ſo loftie a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, he left it neuertheleſse ſo farre aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that it has been eaſie for his ſucceſſours to proſecute the ſame. See now the <hi>Maximes</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19849:8"/>
obſerued hitherto as <hi>Oracles,</hi> which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the true <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is grounded vpon <hi>Religion,</hi> as that which for conſcience ſake does make people vndertake any thing. There ought to be tes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> a great zeale to the <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> that he might ſerue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of it in his deſignes. And he ought to make the Pope conceiue, that to fauour the greatneſse of <hi>Spaine</hi> in ruining the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> is the ſupport of his owne authoritie, and puiſſance. It behooues him to perſwade the other <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Italie,</hi> that on the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>Spaine</hi> depends the vpholding of the <hi>Church</hi> againſt any other power. And that the entrance of <hi>Strangers</hi> into Italie be barred, to conſerue the Religion, which could not but be ſoyled by ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France,</hi> where there be <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and where the <hi>Catholikes</hi> are the <hi>Maſters,</hi> He should incite the <hi>King</hi> to banishe thoſe, and ſolicite the <hi>Pope</hi> to vrge the ſame, yet giuing vnderhand courage and aſſiſtance to the ſaid <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to ſtirre vp there a <hi>Ciuill war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19849:8"/>
which might ſo much the more weaken the Kingdome. If the <hi>King</hi> pereiuing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie of this counſell, will not giue eare to it, He ought then to ſtirre vp the <hi>Catholikes</hi> themſelues againſt him, as againſt a fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Heretiks:</hi> to aſſiſt them alſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and therein likewiſe to engage the <hi>Pope,</hi> if he can. For in what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner ſoeuer, he should procure that this Realme be deſtroyed of it ſelfe, as that which euerie where ſets it ſelfe againſt the deſigne of the <hi>Spanish Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>England</hi> where the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> where they beare the ſway, he ought to make peace in any wiſe with this Realme, to the end that through the power it hath at Sea, it doe not incommodate the <hi>Indies,</hi> where his chiefe treaſures are. And that vnder this apparant amitie he may the more eaſily ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelfe <hi>Protector</hi> of the <hi>Catholickes</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Wherefore he ought to aduantage himſelfe by the <hi>Colledges</hi> founded of purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in <hi>Flanders</hi> and in <hi>Spaine,</hi> to inſtruct the <hi>English youth</hi> in the <hi>Catholicke Religion,</hi> inciting them to come thither by the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19849:9"/>
there vſed, and to follow their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies there, without paying any thing. Where the <hi>Diuinitie</hi> they learne, is to acquire <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome,</hi> and merit heauen, in ſeruing the greatneſse of <hi>Spaine,</hi> at the coſt of their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie,</hi> where (though the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> be a <hi>Catholicke</hi>) the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> share ſo well the authoritie, that <hi>he</hi> needs to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>Empire</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> (being the ſame with <hi>Spaine</hi>) as the ſole bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and he should augment it from their ſpoyles, vnder preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of <hi>Religion,</hi> and a deſire thereby to defend <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> againſt the <hi>Turke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where the power is shared between two <hi>Religions, he</hi> ought to anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te one ſide againſt the other, giuing hope to the <hi>Catholickes</hi> of the ſpoyle of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and holding them in breath, to make them breake as occaſion shall ſerue.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> where the <hi>Catholic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes</hi> haue not any power, and where ſo long and bloodie warres haue not been able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this people vnder the yoake of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19849:9"/>
the endeauour should be, to make them lay downe their armes through a long truce, and in this repoſe, to foment a <hi>Schiſme</hi> there, which may diuide them betwixt themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</p>
               <p>To manage well theſe affaires, one muſt come to the second point, that conſiſts in the manner to maintaine ſuch intelligences as shall be neceſſarie in all other <hi>States,</hi> which <hi>he</hi> muſt doe by the meanes of <hi>Embaſſadours</hi> as perſons towards whom reſpect is borne. Likewiſe by <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Preachers</hi> that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue great power in their pulpits and alſo in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular families, by <hi>Money,</hi> whereby men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>Confidents,</hi> ſuch on whoſe truſt one may relie, and herein he muſt not be ſparing. Aboue all, he muſt eſſay to gaine the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> to diuert the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous deſignes which they might haue againſt <hi>Spaine;</hi> Or elſe to render them odious who are found too faithfull, and ruine them in any wiſe howſoeuer.</p>
               <p>The third point toucheth <hi>negociations</hi> and <hi>treaties,</hi> wherein he muſt employ perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>patient,</hi> He muſt all way shewe a deſire of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19849:10"/>
peace, thereby to caſt others aſleepe, and in the meane time prepare himſelfe to warre, for to ſurpriſe them vnprouided.</p>
               <p>If there happen any difference between two <hi>pettie Princes,</hi> he ought to interpoſe himſelfe for their agreement, either as <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge</hi> of <hi>Arbitratour,</hi> and to haue <hi>in depoſito,</hi> in truſt (if he can) that which is in debate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, incenſing them (if he can) in ſtead of appeaſing them, conſentig with the one to diuide the ſpoiles of the other, and vpon the diuiſion diſpoſſeſſe both two. He ought, not to looſe any occaſion of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling in the affaires of his neighbours, but yet exclude others from medling with his. Eſpecially the <hi>French</hi> from the affaires of <hi>Italie,</hi> hindering them from hauing any entrance there, becauſe they are the onely men that may fruſtrate the deſignes of <hi>Spaine</hi> in that Country.</p>
               <p>The fourth point conſiſts in being <hi>allwaies powerfully armed,</hi> which is an aſſured meanes to keepe his Subjects in obedience, and his Neighbours in reſpect, to preuent the deſignes of his enemies, to ſurpriſe them if they sleep,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19849:10"/>
and to take his owne aduantage from vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected occaſions.</p>
               <p>The fifth point is <hi>reputation,</hi> and although that it dependeth on the foure firſt, neuer the leſſe being ſimply conſidered, it eſtablisheth a fifth maxime, whereby <hi>Spaine</hi> gaineth as much, as by any of the reſt. Conſidering that the opinion conceiued of her great zeale for the maintenance of the Catholicke Religion, couers with the cloake of pietie, all her other deſignes, and holds the people in a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full awe. The feare of her profound intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences throughout, cauſeth other <hi>Princes</hi> to haue a care that they engage not themſelues lightly againſt her. This aſsurance confirmed in mens vnderſtandings, by ſo much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of her prudent dexteritie, (knowing how to aduantage herſelfe in Treaties) inuites her inferiours to enter more forwardly in league with her, and to ſet themſelues vnder her shade. The eſtate of her <hi>armes</hi> allwaies on foote, conſumes thoſe that are ſuſpicious of her, and aſſures others that depend on her protection.</p>
               <p>From all theſe things reſults the reputation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19849:11"/>
of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Her <hi>intereſt</hi> is, to manage well <hi>this pietie.</hi> And though all <hi>Princes</hi> hold for a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall maxime, that they should carefully conſerue their reputation, <hi>Spaine</hi> ought to be ſo much the more jealous thereof, as her deſignes are greater then thoſe of other <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This huge frame compoſed of ſo many parts, and as it were incumbered with its owne weight, moues by its ſecret ſprings, which looſe their force euen as they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19849:11"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST OF FRANCE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>RANCE being ſeated betweene the <hi>Alpes</hi> and the <hi>Pyrenean moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> and flanked by two <hi>ſeas,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to be inuited by <hi>nature</hi> to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſelfe againſt the proceeding of this puiſſant Neighbourhood. For <hi>shee</hi> appeares like a banke againſt this <hi>torrent,</hi> and the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of her ſituation is ſuch, that shee may hinder the diſtribution of the <hi>head</hi> to the <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>Monarchie</hi> which does oppugne her. But this being not ſufficient to croſſe the proceedings of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is, to take all the <hi>counter-courſe</hi> (to impeach all shee may her deſignes) by <hi>maximes,</hi> which wee come now deliuer vnto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19849:12"/>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>fourth,</hi> (vpon whom the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of all theſe ſubtilties has been exerciſed euen to the vtmoſt point) hauing better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood them then any other before him, (for that he proued them more) he firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the true intereſt of <hi>France,</hi> which is to thwart or counterpoint <hi>Spaine</hi> in all theſe points.</p>
               <p>In ſuch wiſe that if the firſt maxime of the intereſt of <hi>Spaine</hi> be, to perſecute the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> for to growe by their ſpoyles: the firſt of the intereſt of <hi>France</hi> is, to make the <hi>Catholickes</hi> perceiue the venome hidden vndes the same. Eſpecially to let the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> vnderſtand that the hopes which <hi>Spaine</hi> giues her to augment her treaſures by the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is not but to further her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne towards the <hi>Monarchie,</hi> where shee can no ſooner arriue, but the <hi>Pope</hi> muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her <hi>Seruant,</hi> whereas his authoritie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer has more luſtre, then when the power of <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> is ballanced. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouer <hi>France</hi> should make shew to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> that allthough shee be of a <hi>diuerſe Religion</hi> to theirs, yet shee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19849:12"/>
would rather their <hi>conuerſion,</hi> then their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> aſſuring them that this shall not at all hinder her that shee contribute not of her owne to conſerue them, and to aide them freely againſt all thoſe that would trouble or change any thing in their <hi>States</hi> and <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe as the ſecond <hi>maxime</hi> of the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> is to aduantage her deſigne through intelligences. The ſecond of the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is, not to sleepe at all in hers. Nor to ſpare money in <hi>ſpies</hi> and <hi>penſioners,</hi> to the end to know what paſſeth amongſt her <hi>neighbours,</hi> and that as occaſion ſerues, shee ſtrengthen the weake, aſsure the fearefull, ſtop the engagement of thoſe that are moued to decline, retire thoſe that are allready en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, and that shee croſſe in all places and by all meanes the <hi>intelligences</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the third <hi>maxime,</hi> which concerns <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gociation.</hi> It ought not to be ſuffered, that <hi>Spaine</hi> meddle in any <hi>Treatie,</hi> but that <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> alſo ſtep between on her part. Eſpecially in <hi>Italie,</hi> where shee would be ſole judge and <hi>vmpire.</hi> That which shee will be, if <hi>France</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19849:13"/>
were not aſſured of one <hi>port</hi> to enter there, which shee ought to keepe, euen ſo long as shee will oppoſe the others greatneſſe, and be conſidered as the bullwarke of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie. Moreouer <hi>flegmaticke perſonnes</hi> ought to be made choice of (for <hi>to treate with Spaine,</hi>) and ſuch as haue not any impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient humour, whereof the <hi>French</hi> nation is accuſed, to the end, to take away their hope of profiting by <hi>delaies,</hi> wherewith <hi>Spaine</hi> has been accuſtomed to wearie all the world.</p>
               <p>To the fourth Maxime. There ought to be oppoſed force to force. For neither per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, nor the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of armes will awe him thats armed. So as that France ought to cutt off all vnneceſſarie expences, and be all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies powerfully armed, hauing ſufficiently to doe the ſame, without borrowing elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <hi>ſoldiers, munition, and money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſo be that the aboue named <hi>maximes</hi> be well obſerued, the reputation of <hi>Spaine,</hi> (whereby shee doth ſo aduantageously pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile) will be abated: that of <hi>France</hi> eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and the other <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19849:13"/>
ſeeing ſuch a <hi>counterpoiſe</hi> to affaires, will againe take courage, and without appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of future danger will voluntarily embrace the cauſe of their conſeruation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19849:14"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST, OF THE PRINCES OF ITALIE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>TALIE, which is enuironned with the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean ſea,</hi> (after the deluge of thoſe <hi>barbarous nations</hi> that ſo long time afflicted it) ſeemed as if shee ought to thinke of nothing more then to benefit herſelfe by the opportunitie of her ſituation, to keep her selfe <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>ſecret,</hi> being as well ſeparated by the <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces,</hi> as diuided by her ſituation. And truly it was then the <hi>maxime</hi> which shee ought to hold. For theſe <hi>little Princes</hi> might liue preaceably vnder the shadow of the <hi>greater,</hi> when hauing amongſt themſelues their juſt counterpoiſe, they cannot attempt any thing vpon their inferiours. And the <hi>principall Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19849:14"/>
sharing amongſt themſelues the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſuch a Countrey, had reaſon to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude their neighbours from the Knowledge of their affaires.</p>
               <p>But ſince that the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath ſet footing in <hi>Italie,</hi> and that finding himſelfe <hi>Maiſter</hi> of <hi>both ends</hi> thereof, he has made the ballance incline on his owne ſide, the true intereſt in generall of the <hi>Italian Princes</hi> has beene to keep euer one gate (at leaſt) open, to guard themſelues from the oppreſſion which ſuch a formidable <hi>Power</hi> might make them feare.</p>
               <p>And although that for this effect they ought to hold intelligences with other <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> it behooues them notwithſtanding, to doe it cheifely with the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> for three reaſons. <hi>Firſt,</hi> for the neereneſſe, and opportunitie of being able to ſuccour them, either by <hi>ſea</hi> or <hi>land. Secondly,</hi> for the great forces that this great <hi>Realme</hi> can ſet on foote. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> by this bridle to reſtraine the <hi>Spainard,</hi> who otherwiſe would carrie himſelfe towards them with leſſe modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19849:15"/>The other <hi>maxime</hi> which <hi>Italie</hi> ought to obſerue is, to conſerue her ſelfe in <hi>peace, Firſt,</hi> becauſe there can be noe warre, but the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> will <hi>there</hi> take part, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as fauouring one of the parties, or elſe as <hi>Arbitrators.</hi> Beſides it ought to be conſidered, that warre cannot be enkindled in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, without great danger of ſtirring vp di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe humours, which doe now lie ſtill.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the two points wherein lieth the <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>Italie</hi> in generall. And although that euery <hi>Prince</hi> ought to haue the ſame <hi>aime,</hi> there are notwithſtanding certaine <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſts</hi> in each State. The <hi>Common</hi>-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> in regard of the extent of her dominion both by <hi>ſea</hi> and <hi>land,</hi> likewiſe of the firmeneſſe of her eſtablishment for twlue <hi>ages</hi> entire, and of the prudent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſo wiſe a gouernment, is without doubt the chiefe <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Italie</hi> next that of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> And shee alſo has been the <hi>firſt Common-wealth</hi> that has ſetled the rules of her conſeruation, and that has moſt punctually obſerued them, in taking for her particular intereſt, that of <hi>Italie</hi> in generall.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19849:15"/>
Moreouer for particular reſpects <hi>shee</hi> makes it a <hi>maxime,</hi> to hold a ſtrait intelligence with the <hi>Turke,</hi> and for the ſame shee spares not any coſt. Shee belieues alſo that her <hi>intereſt</hi> is, to maintaine warre abroad and <hi>foment</hi> the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with money. That which the other <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of <hi>Italie</hi> ought alſo to doe, if they had ſtrength and courage to vndertake it.</p>
               <p>Shee looſes noe time for to hinder the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> from waxing great. The <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> ſeemes extraordinarily jealous of theſe two <hi>Potentates,</hi> though it be a <hi>maxime</hi> common to all <hi>Princes</hi> to hinder the growth of their <hi>Neighbours.</hi> As for the other <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Italie,</hi> shee vpholds them according to her owne benefit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19849:16"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST, OF THE SEA OF ROME.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is, firſt to procure by all manner of meanes the diminution of the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Church lands</hi> ly ſo fitt for her, that if once the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> come to quitt the ſpecious pretext that he has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to protect the <hi>holie</hi> Sea, certainly he will eaſily appropriate all this goodly demaine, for to joyne together the <hi>two ends,</hi> which allready belong vnto him.</p>
               <p>The puiſſance of the <hi>Venetians</hi> and of the <hi>great Duke</hi> does much enfeeble that of the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which without theſe obſtacles would commaund the <hi>two Gulfes.</hi> So shee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19849:16"/>
ought to deſire that theſe two <hi>Princes</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne at leaſt as they be.</p>
               <p>But all theſe are but generall <hi>maximes.</hi> There be yet three particular of the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is, to maintaine her credit throughout, by the meanes of <hi>Eecleſiaſticall perſonnes,</hi> as the <hi>ſinnewes</hi> of her greatneſs, whom shee ought to <hi>protect</hi> againſt the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> is, to make <hi>Princes</hi> dread the thunder-bolt of <hi>excommunications,</hi> But not to vſe it too oft, for feare they come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>third</hi> is, to reſtraine the Popes as much as may be, hindering them from making great their <hi>houſes</hi> at the <hi>Churches</hi> coſt, or committing any extrauagance by their <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> prejudiciall to the common good of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be to no purpoſe to touch the intereſt of the other <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Italie,</hi> for that they are either ſo little <hi>conſiderable</hi> as they can doe nothing of themſelues: or elſe ſo <hi>subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> as they dare not make shew of any other intereſt, then that of <hi>thoſe</hi> on whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19849:17"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST OF THE DVKE OF SAVOY.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T remaines onely for conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to ſpeake of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> The <hi>Eſtate</hi> of this <hi>Prince</hi> is in ſuch manner ſituated, that to which ſide ſoeuer he turnes, he is of great importance to the partie he embraceth. CHARLES EMANVEL (who was firſt willing to make knowne that a <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Sauoy</hi> could make <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>warre</hi> in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> beleeued, that the intereſt of his <hi>Eſtate</hi> was, to ſide one while with <hi>France,</hi> another while with <hi>Spaine,</hi> according to the occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and good of his affaires, which was the ſole <hi>but</hi> of his deſignes, without thinking of <hi>Treaties</hi> made either with the one or the other. But this <hi>Prince,</hi> full of vaſt thoughts
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19849:17"/>
(and who could not bound his <hi>ambition</hi> by the barriers that Nature had ſet to his <hi>Eſtate</hi>) was glad that the ſituation of his <hi>Country</hi> might ſerue for a pretext to his <hi>diſquiet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For indeed the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Sauoy</hi> is, to haue allwaies a good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with <hi>France,</hi> becauſe <hi>shee</hi> can aſsiſt him with the whole maſse of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, againſt <hi>one member</hi> of the power of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who hath more jealouſie of her <hi>Eſtates</hi> in <hi>Italie,</hi> then (to ſay in a manner) of all the reſt together, hauing alſo a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire to joyne <hi>Piemont</hi> to the <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Milaine.</hi> So as, the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Sauoy</hi> should beleeue, that what amitie soeuer he has with <hi>Spaine,</hi> it is moſt dangerous to him. He ought neuertheleſſe to entertaine it, in ſo much as it is needfull to gard him from <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19849:18"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST OF GERMANIE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS huge maſse of <hi>Prouinces</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together, inuironned with <hi>three Seas,</hi> and diuided by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mightie riuers, has beene heretofore the terrour of the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> which at length shee hath tranſported to her selfe. And as <hi>before,</hi> shee had noe other intereſt but her <hi>libertie:</hi> so <hi>ſince,</hi> shee has no other deſigne but to conſerue the ſame. For truly if the name of <hi>Empire</hi> has brought ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and reputation to <hi>Germanie,</hi> it hath giuen her in recompence much jealouſie and diſtrus. Shee preſently diſcouered her <hi>Emperours,</hi> and eſſayed to limit their power for feare that from Chiefs of this Country, they come to be Maſters thereof. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19849:18"/>
being ſuch a daintie morcell that the moſt temperate cannot forbeare it. This notwithſtanding, by the continuance of certaine ſucceſſions, the <hi>Empire</hi> being eſtablished in the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> (that of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which is the principall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thereof) knew to manage this begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of eſtablishment with ſuch dexteritie, that now it ſeemes as hereditarie in that <hi>houſe.</hi> The maxime of <hi>Germanie</hi> was to hinder the progreſſe of this vſurpation. And now her intereſt is, to reduce things to their former eſtate, by diſtributing this honour intercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geably to the principall houſes, and reſtraining the power of the Emperours, whoſe <hi>counſell</hi> ought to be the <hi>generall Diets,</hi> to conſult alltogether of the meanes to conſerue the common libertie, and to reſiſt the <hi>Turke,</hi> who is the onely force that <hi>Germanie</hi> should be afraid of.</p>
               <p>The diuerſitie of <hi>Religion</hi> ought not to cauſe any diuerſitie of opinion in things that concerne the common good. The <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of all the <hi>Princes</hi> in generall and of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19849:19"/>
euery one of them in particular is, mutually to defend and jointly to hinder that the <hi>Emperour</hi> make not an attempt vpon the libertie of any, vnder what pretext ſoeuer it be. They should likewiſe take heed that the <hi>ſtronger</hi> amongſt them oppreſſe not the weaker, whereto the <hi>Emperour</hi> will all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies lend a hand, for to gaine by the ruine both of the one and the other.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Catholicke Princes</hi> ought from hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceforth to diſabuſe themſelues, and to hold for certaine, that vnder the colour of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they ſerue the deſigne of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and forge by little and little the irons of their owne bondage, being not able to hope for any other aduantage then to be the <hi>laſt</hi> ruined.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (ſince they alone cannot withſtand ſo great forces) should make it a <hi>maxime,</hi> to be firſt well vnited at home, and afterwards to hold neceſſarie intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences abroad, for to counterpoiſe the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke</hi> league. Their chiefeſt aime should be, to abide ſtreightly conjoind together, and to beleeue, that their aſsured ruine lieth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19849:19"/>
in their <hi>diſunion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the aduantages propoſed vnto them for to <hi>diſunite</hi> them one from another, ought to be the bands of their concord and good intelligence.</p>
               <p>This is the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germanie</hi> and of the <hi>Imperiall townes,</hi> which they neuer ought to relinquish, For without this ſupport, they will beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the prey of the firſt <hi>Vſurper,</hi> and their great <hi>magazins</hi> and ſtately <hi>Arcenalls</hi> will ſerue for a lure to intice thoſe that are <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of the field.</p>
               <p>There are <hi>foure</hi> Kingdomes which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend in a manner vpon <hi>Germanie</hi> and are obliged to follow the fortune of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Hungarie</hi> for diuers inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts remaine tyed to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Swedeland</hi> embrace the partie that maintaines the libertie of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> fearing their owne may be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, after this comes to be oppreſsed.</p>
               <p>It is requiſite that <hi>Germanie</hi> remaine ſtrictly vnited with both theſe Realmes,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19849:20"/>
But the latter shee can neuer forſake, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout an eternall blot of ingratitude, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued from thence euen that which was beyond her hopes, ſeeing her selfe all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie swallowed in the very gulfe of ſo hard a bondage, when this King (shewed onely to the world through ſo many darke clowdes) made the Sunne of her deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce appeare to this deſolate Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19849:20"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST OF THE SWISSES AND OF THE VNITED PROVINCES of the Low-Countries.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the two ſides of <hi>Germanie,</hi> at the entrie of this large Country, there are formed two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weathes dreadfull amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the other powers of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> both for the valour of their people, and for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of their ſituation. So that very rightly one may call them the two armes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The right arme is <hi>Switzerland,</hi> the left is the <hi>Vnited State</hi> of the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> The one is amongſt the rockes and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pices; the other amongſt the Seas and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes. The one domineers in the <hi>Alpes:</hi> and the other in the <hi>Ocean.</hi> The naturall diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19849:21"/>
of both theſe people is ſo agreeable to the nature of the Countries which they inhabite, as that the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> ſeeme made for the Mountaines, and the Mountai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for the <hi>Swiſſes.</hi> The <hi>Sea</hi> for the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llanders:</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> for the <hi>Sea.</hi> In <hi>Switzer-land</hi> euery <hi>Canton,</hi> in the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> euery <hi>Prouince</hi> is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. The <hi>Swiſſes</hi> sell the libertie of their bodies to others, and doe guard the libertie of their country: the <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</hi> ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d their owne libertie intire. Long <hi>peace</hi> hath enriched <hi>thoſe:</hi> but <hi>theſe</hi> flourish by the continuation of <hi>warre.</hi> The intereſt of the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> is <hi>Peace:</hi> but the <hi>Hollanders</hi> should hold for an aſſured maxime, to be alwaies in <hi>Armes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two <hi>Republikes</hi> cannot make bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alliance for their ſubſiſtence then with <hi>France,</hi> who (to oppoſe <hi>Spaine</hi>) does en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the <hi>Suiſses</hi> with her money, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the <hi>Hollanders</hi> with her Counſell and Armes.</p>
               <p>Theſe two Powers should neuer be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19849:21"/>
betwixt themſelues, either through <hi>iealouſie,</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> ſince theſe are the ſole maladies that may extinguish them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19849:22"/>
               <head>OF THE INTEREST, OF ENGLAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ngland which is as a little world apart, had not any thing to doe with other <hi>Princes,</hi> but onely ſo far as the neceſſitie of commerce did oblige her, which was then her true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. For thereby shee gained great riches, which together with her ſituation, haue made her of very great account. But ſince that vnder the shadow of that miſterious mariage betweene PHILIP and MARIE, the <hi>practiſes</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> are inſenſibly slipped in, <hi>England</hi> (which before had <hi>maximes</hi> conformable to her owne ſelfe) is by litle and litle accommodated ſometimes to the intereſt of <hi>France</hi> and ſometimes to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queene</hi> ELIZABETH (who by her
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19849:22"/>
prudent gouernment has equall'd the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi>) shee knowing well the diſpoſition of her <hi>State,</hi> beleeued that the true intereſt thereof conſiſted, <hi>Firſt</hi> in holding a firme vnion in it ſelfe, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheiuing to ſmother the reliques of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent factions, deeming (as it is moſt true) that <hi>England is a mightie Animal, which can neuer dye except it kill it selfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shee grounded this fundamentall maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, <hi>to banish thence the exerciſe of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as the onely meanes to breake all the plots of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this pretext, did there foment Rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And allthough shee profeſsed her ſelfe very much obliged to <hi>Philip,</hi> towards who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> shee bare euer a ſpeciall regard, neuertheleſſe shee had ſo carefull a conſideration of the intereſt of her <hi>State,</hi> that shee beleeued it was neuer fitt to conclude a peace with him, for three very euident reaſons. The <hi>firſt</hi> was, for to weaken the power that shee ſuſpected in the Indies: The <hi>ſecond,</hi> for to enrich her Realme by depredations: The <hi>third,</hi> thereby to make her Subjects warlike,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19849:23"/>
and keep them in perpetuall exerciſe for <hi>Sea-fight,</hi> which is the <hi>defence</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>Shee beleeued that the intereſt of her <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> was, to aide <hi>France,</hi> and releeue it, leaſt that by the fall thereof shee ſuffer thoſe to waxe great, from whom shee had cauſe to defend her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>By the ſame <hi>maxime, Shee</hi> ſupported the springing libertie of the <hi>Vnited-Prouinces,</hi> whoſe protection againſt the puiſsance of <hi>Spaine,</hi> is one of the principall points of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands intereſt,</hi> as well becauſe shee thereby weakens a too powerfull Neighbour: as for that <hi>Protection</hi> ſerues ſometimes for a ſtep to reach ſome higher matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shee</hi> held moſt ſtrait intelligences with the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> for reaſons allto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether peculiar to <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shee</hi> did the ſame (though for other reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects) with the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all theſe maximes <hi>this wiſe Princeſse</hi> has very well made knowne to her <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours,</hi> that beſides the <hi>Intereſt</hi> which the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has common with all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19849:23"/>
                  <hi>Princes,</hi> he has yet <hi>one particular,</hi> which is, that <hi>He ought throughly to acquire the adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement of the Proteſtant Religion, euen with as much zeale as the King of Spaine appeares Protectour of the Catholike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this effect, <hi>England</hi> should haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences throughout, where ſoeuer it is fitting, and take part in all the Treaties that are made with <hi>Proteſtant Princes.</hi> Shee should likewiſe be <hi>allwaies armed,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thereby conſiderable.</p>
               <p>Here is the true intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> which being well followed will eſtablish a third <hi>Puiſſance in</hi> Chriſtendome.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19849:24"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE INTEREST OF THE PRINCES AND STATES of Chriſtendome.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER the ſtablishing of the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of each <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> it ought to be made appeare by the recitall of the principall affaires agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated in <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>fifth</hi> yeares paſt, how the ill ſucceſſes that haue therein happened, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from any other cauſe then the neglecting of the ſaid <hi>intereſt.</hi> For to teach vs that <hi>in matter of State</hi> one ought not to ſuffer himſelfe to be led by <hi>inordinate
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19849:24"/>
deſires,</hi> which carrie vs oftentimes to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take things beyond our ſtrength: nor by <hi>violent paſsions</hi> which doe diuersly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs, according as wee are poſſeſſed the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith: nor by <hi>ſuperſtitious opinions,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ill-conceiued ſcruples are miniſtred vnto vs, but rather by our proper intereſt guided by reaſon alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, which ought to be the rule of our actions, to the end that by ſuch examples, wee ſeeing (as in a mirrour) the faultes of others, may thereby benefit our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19849:25"/>
               <head>THE FIRST DISCOVRSE VPON THE AFFAIRE of the League.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>NDER the Raignes of <hi>Francis</hi> the ſecond and <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, <hi>France</hi> was exceedingly moleſted with ciuill warres, the <hi>youth</hi> of theſe two <hi>Princes</hi> was the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall cauſe thereof. Each would haue the managing of affaires. A conteſtation was betwixt Queene <hi>Catherine</hi> their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the <hi>Princes</hi> of the blood, and vnder them, the houſes wich had moſt power, were thoſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morancy,</hi> which had quietly ruled <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> their Father. <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Lorraine</hi> Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> bore the partie of <hi>Catherine. Annas</hi> Duke of <hi>Montmorancy</hi> tooke part with the <hi>Princes</hi> of the blood. Likewiſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19849:25"/>
there was amongſt them difference of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. The warres about Religion were great and bloodie, and laſted euen to the death of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>ninth,</hi> and his brother <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>third</hi> ſucceeded him. He was of age capable to gouerne, he had goodly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and gaue hopes of a happy Reigne.</p>
               <p>At his comming to the Crowne <hi>Henry</hi> teſtified a deſire to lead a peaceable life, but it was rather for to plunge himſelfe in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse and pleaſures, then to reigne well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (ſonne of <hi>Francis</hi>) a Prince endowed with great qualities, and full of loftie thoughts, ſeeing the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Brother</hi> without children, and the firſt Princes of the blood to make profeſſion of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, is bold to aſpire vnto the <hi>Royaltie,</hi> and to gett thither, makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Protecteur of the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and the Perſecutour of the <hi>Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> againſt whom he ſtirred vp diuers warres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon, King</hi> of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> firſt Prince of the blood, Chief of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> partie and a Prince adorned with an heroïque vertue, ſucceſsfully waged diuers
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19849:26"/>
warres in fauour of the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here be <hi>three</hi> Henry's, Chiefs of three ſeueral parties in <hi>France,</hi> who haue euery one their intereſt. The <hi>King</hi> to maintaine his lawfull authoritie. The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to poſſeſſe the Kings place, and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nauarre</hi> to hinder the King of <hi>France</hi> his ruine, which was indeed his owne, and of his partie which made him ſubſiſt in reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The firſt of theſe through weakeneſse lets himſelfe be induced to make warre vpon the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nauarre.</hi> The ſecond makes himſelfe Head of the <hi>Catholike</hi> partie. The third becomes Protectour of the <hi>Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</hi> So that as <hi>he</hi> who ought to haue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded others, is very happie to haue place one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the partie of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who therein came so farre with him, that when he was kill'd in the yeare 1588. he was vpon the point to make him be declared to the States of the Realme, incapable to reigne, and the Princes of the blood to ſucceed him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philipp</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who had allwaies an eye open to his great deſigne, foments
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19849:26"/>
this buſineſse, fauours the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> helps him with money in <hi>France,</hi> lets him not want for any thing, and euen after his death continues his aſſiſtance to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Mayne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>King</hi> ſeeing himſelfe abandonn'd of all the great Townes of his Realme, and of the moſt part of his Nobilitie, caſts himſelfe into the armes of the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> who by his aſſiſtance retireth him almoſt from the hands of his enemies, which held him beſieged within <hi>Tours,</hi> he brings him as triumphant, before his Capitall Cittie of <hi>Paris,</hi> where by the ſtab of a knife he dyed and left the Kingdome to the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre,</hi> in the yeare 1589.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Prince</hi> ſeeing himſelfe eleuated to so high a dignitie, was inuited by the change of his condition to make change of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and quitting that which he had held euen till then, he embraced that of <hi>France.</hi> He had great oppoſitions cauſed by <hi>Philip,</hi> as well by his practiſes at <hi>Rome,</hi> as by his aſſiſtance to the <hi>League</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> allwaies vnder pretext of his great zeale for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19849:27"/>
Religion. During the time that <hi>Henry</hi> is a Proteſtant, <hi>Philip</hi> maintaines that he cannot reigne, cauſeth him to be excommunicated, his Subjects to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed from the oath of allegeance, ſetteth his kingdome in prey, that by this meanes he might gett it as eaſily as <hi>Ferdinand</hi> got the Kingdome of <hi>Nauarre</hi> from his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſour. When he giues hope to turne Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, <hi>Philip</hi> declareth that he is an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and that hauing beene relapſed, he can neuer lawfully reigne, he aideth his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with money and armes ſufficient to weaken both parties, but not to ruine the one in ſuch ſort, as that the other might ſubſiſt without him, willing to wearie them whom he maintained, to the end that they should be conſtrained to giue themſelues vp to him.</p>
               <p>Henry on his part shewes vnto Queene ELIZABETH, and the <hi>Vnited Prouinces,</hi> with the Proteſtants of <hi>Germanie</hi> and the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> what intereſt they had all in the cauſe, He receiued great aſſiſtance from them all, and euen ſecretly from <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19849:27"/>
great Duke of <hi>Tuſcanie,</hi> a Prince of great vnderſtanding, and who judged that the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of <hi>France</hi> to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> was to ſubject all the other Princes. But the Republike of <hi>Venice</hi> onely amongſt all the <hi>Catholike States,</hi> did without delay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him King of <hi>France,</hi> after the death of his Predeceſſour. So wellas with all theſe aides, and his owne valour, he reſis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the very beginning, and afterwards hauing obtained diuers victories, and his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires beginning to proſper, he was conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a great Prince.</p>
               <p>From thence forward the <hi>People</hi> wearie of their miſeries, beganne to diſabuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to giue no more ſuch credence as they had done, to their <hi>Preachers:</hi> the <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> to thinke vpon the ſide that proſper'd: the <hi>Gouernours</hi> of Townes to aſſure their affaires with the <hi>ſtrongeſt:</hi> and the Principalls of the <hi>partie</hi> to conſerue what dignitie ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they had beene raiſed vnto. All theſe commotions cauſed the <hi>Leaguers</hi> to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the States.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> takes occaſion from ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19849:28"/>
for to perſwade them, that the onely remedie to reſtablish their affaires was to chooſe a King, and offers his daughter to him whom they choſe. <hi>This</hi> was the apple of diſcord. The Duke of <hi>Mayne,</hi> principall Commaunder, could not pretend to haue her, he being allreadie married, nor would ſuffer that another should, leſt himſelfe from being <hi>Maſter,</hi> should become a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</hi> His Nephew the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was inticed with this daintie bit. The Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> his Vnkle had as good an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite as he. The Duke of <hi>Mercueur</hi> pretended the Dutchie of <hi>Britanie</hi> to belong to him by his Wife. The eldeſt ſonne of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> as head of the familie, was alſo mentioned. So that <hi>Philip</hi> thought by this diſcord to draw them to make choice of <hi>him.</hi> While theſe things were a doing, <hi>Henry</hi> turnes <hi>Catholike.</hi> This change made ſome of the principall Townes and Gouernours to declare themſelues on his parte, and the other beganne to treate in the Court of <hi>Rome. Philip</hi> neglects nothing (no more then the chiefeſt <hi>Leaguers</hi>) for to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19849:28"/>
impeache that <hi>Henry</hi> be not acknowledged a <hi>good Catholike,</hi> and a long time hindered his Ambaſsadour from hauing Audience.</p>
               <p>At the length <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. (then <hi>Pope</hi>) ſeeing well that he was eſtablishing himſelfe without him, reſolued to graunt that which he could not hinder, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him for <hi>King,</hi> it being <hi>à maxime</hi> of <hi>Rome, to gouerne according to euents,</hi> to the end that shee looſe not that reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and reſpect, which Shee endeauours throughly to preſerue, and without which her autoritie would be but a small matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> fallen from ſuch an hope, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues his aſſiſtance neuertheleſse to the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the <hi>Leaguers,</hi> Beſides he inciteth <hi>Emanuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> (at that time his ſonne-in-law) to ſet vpon <hi>Prouence,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diuert him from the purſuite of his claime to the <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Milaine</hi> in right of his wife's dowrie. <hi>Henry</hi> ſeeing this obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie, declares himſelfe openly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth warre againſt <hi>Philip.</hi> The ſucceſse thereof was various, and yet after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie of <hi>Amiens</hi> by <hi>Henry, Philip</hi> ſeeing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19849:29"/>
himſelfe very neere his graue, his <hi>Sonne</hi> yong, and <hi>Henry</hi> in the vigour of his age, he reſolued on a peace, which was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at <hi>Veruins,</hi> the yeare 1597. wherein he reſtoreth all that he held of <hi>France,</hi> and then died.</p>
               <p>It behooueth now to conſider the <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Princes</hi> inueloped in this <hi>affaire,</hi> what faultes they therein committed, and what were the euents thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> whoſe intereſt conſis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in not ſuffering diuerſe factions in his Kingdome, in preſeruing the Princes of the blood ſince he had noe children of his owne and in keeping vnder thoſe which lifted vp themſelues to the prejudice of his <hi>Royall authoritie,</hi> yet he did quite contrarie. For he fomented the said factions in ſtead of extinguishing them, and euen joined with the one to deſtroy the other. He made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall warre vpon the Princes of the blood, at the perſuaſion of thoſe who deſired to ſee their ruine for to raiſe themſelues in their places, and he authorized in the commaund of his armies thoſe that aſpired to the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19849:29"/>
of his Kingdome. He did yet worſe, for when he beganne to perceiue their plot, he would preuent it by a remedie which wrought his owne deſtruction, to wit, by caſting himſelfe into an affected and vnu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall deuotion, not ſtirring from the Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Monkes,</hi> thinking by this meanes to take from the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> the credit that he had gotten amongſt the <hi>Catholickes,</hi> who held him for their Chief. But there arriued the contrarie, for he became contemptible to his people, who chaſed him from his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> and all the great Townes of his Kingdome reuolted from him, they also reduced him to ſuch a pitifull caſe, that in the end a <hi>Monke</hi> had the boldneſſe to kill him, which was the fruite of his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and ill conduct.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſucceeding a <hi>Father</hi> and and <hi>Vnkle,</hi> both great perſonages, and who had had in the precedent Reignes great part in the commaund of Armies, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of affaires, and he thinking himſelfe no whit inferiour to them neither in cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage nor in vertue, conceiues the moſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19849:30"/>
haughtie deſigne that a man (borne the <hi>Subiect</hi> of a <hi>Prince</hi>) could vndertake, that is, to vſurpe the place of his <hi>Souueraigne.</hi> The occaſion ſeemes moſt fauourable to him. He has already this aduantage of gaining by the labour of his <hi>Father,</hi> it being a thing moſt difficult, that the life of one man alone should be able to worke ſuch a change. He incountereth a <hi>King</hi> without children, and of the humour of thoſe, vnder whom ſuch projects might be attempted. He findeth a <hi>Kingdome</hi> rent by factions, and aſsaulted with <hi>the moſt dangerous of all Ciuill warres, which was for the difference of Religion.</hi> He ſees the firſt Princes of the blood in the weakeſt faction, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> readie to aſsiſt all thoſe that trouble <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Popes</hi> intereſsed euery way to perſecute the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> The matter ſtanding thus, he (full of hopes) neglecteth nothing to accomplish his deſigne. He was <hi>a goodly man, gracefull, courteous, liberall,</hi> and <hi>valiant.</hi> He imployes all theſe gifts of nature to inſinuate himſelfe amongſt the <hi>Nobilitie, Gentrie</hi> and <hi>Commonaltie.</hi> He shewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19849:30"/>
very zealous of the Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, not by haunting the <hi>Cloiſters,</hi> and walking thorough the ſtreets in Proceſsion: but by perſecuting the Proteſtants, and declaring himſelfe their mortall Ennemie. He maintaines his intelligences at <hi>Rome</hi> and in <hi>Spaine</hi> allwaies vnder the pretence of Religion. He workes the <hi>Preachers</hi> to ſet him in veneration amongſt the <hi>People,</hi> and to make the King be declared a fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Heretickes, hypocriticall, vicious, and idle. So as by ſuch meanes he had ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated his deſigne euen to the laſt ſtep, when vpon the very point of execution, he was groſſely wanting, both to his intereſt, and to his owne ſelfe, which was in this, that after hauing chaſed his <hi>King</hi> from his chiefe Citie, leuied armes againſt him, made pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike declarations thereof, and then made peace with him as with his equall, yet euen then he intruſted his life to him, when he would haue made him be depoſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being not of that ſort, as it might be permitted to faile twice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> had two parts to act.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19849:31"/>
For whilſt he was onely <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> firſt Prince of the blood, and Protectour of the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> his intereſt was, to imploy all his induſtrie and credit, both within and without the Kingdome, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſaid Proteſtants, to the end that they might defend him. For which purpoſe, he did what he could to hinder the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe</hi> from ſeiſing the <hi>Crowne,</hi> whereunto he had intereſt as <hi>preſumptiue</hi> heire thereof, and to make himſelfe knowne to <hi>Henry</hi> the third, not onely in qualitie of Chief of the Proteſtants, but alſo as firſt Prince of the blood, to whom the intereſt of preſeruing the Kings perſonne and Eſtate, was as deere to him as himſelfe, to the end that at his need he should make noe ſcruple to haue recourſe vnto him. Which ſucceeded ſo well with him, that after the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe</hi> his death and the reuolt of his Kingdome, he had not a more aſſured refuge then to put himſelfe into his hands.</p>
               <p>When he was King of <hi>France,</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooued a great dexteritie to demeane him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſcreetly both towards the <hi>Catholikes,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19849:31"/>
and the <hi>Protestants,</hi> incenſed one againſt the other by ſo long and bloody Ciuill warres. <hi>Theſe</hi> gloried in hauing a King of their Religion: but <hi>thoſe</hi> could not endure the ſame, and threatned to abandon him, if he did not turne to theirs. His buſineſſe now was, to preſerue his <hi>old</hi> friends, and not to looſe the new. He promiſes the one not to refuſe inſtruction: and continues with the other, in the exerciſe of his <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> In the meane while, he ſerues his owne turne of both together, to fight againſt his ennemies. In the tediouſneſſe of theſe warres, euery man was wearied, Many of the <hi>Leaguers</hi> like not a <hi>Spanish</hi> King, but yet they would not haue a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> King. The <hi>Catholikes</hi> that ſerued <hi>Henry,</hi> growing impatient to ſee him continue in <hi>this</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, preſse him to embrace theirs, and come ſo farre as to make a third part againſt him.</p>
               <p>Theſe conſiderations made him reſolue at length to turne his <hi>Religion.</hi> And by this meanes he kept the <hi>Catholikes</hi> that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, thereby alſo he gained newe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19849:32"/>
ones from the partie of the <hi>Leaguers,</hi> and he loſt not the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who he well knew could neuer be taken in the number of his enemies, without deſtroying the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of <hi>Religion</hi> which alone maintained them. So as that this <hi>Prince</hi> complying with the time, knew how to take his aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſo fitly, that he had good ſucceſse in his affaires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philipp</hi> who had a deſigne to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Monarchie,</hi> and imagining that the maine obſtacle which he should therein meet with, was the puiſſance of <hi>France,</hi> he embraces the occaſion offer'd vnto him for to ruine the ſame. He aptly ſerues his purpoſe by the ill gouernment of the <hi>King,</hi> and by the ambition of the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> He inciteth the <hi>firſt</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the Proteſtants out of his Kingdome by which way ſo euer, giueth him his owne example, offereth him his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, publisheth his great zeale at <hi>Rome,</hi> exhorts the <hi>Pope</hi> to ioyne with him in ſuch a purſuite: On the other ſide, he vnderhand exciteth the <hi>ſecond</hi> to continue courageous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19849:32"/>
his deſigne, aſſiſts him with money and Counſell. And by ſuch deuiſes he makes himſelfe eſteemed in <hi>France,</hi> as the chiefeſt prop of their Religion. He makes a diuiſion betwixt the King and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> he authoriſeth the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> amongſt the <hi>Catholikes</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenceth the people againſt the <hi>Princes</hi> of the blood, and remoueth (so much as he can) the the children of the <hi>Familie</hi> from the gouernment of the <hi>Realme,</hi> for to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Strangers</hi> there. No other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diuerteth him from his profound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, he holds <hi>that</hi> allwaies couered vnder the vaile of <hi>Pietie,</hi> and of his great zeale to the <hi>Catholike Religion.</hi> He trauelles there ſtep by ſtep without being impatient through the length of the way, or preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated through any accident. After the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> his death, in ſtead of leauing off the worke, he became more reſolute. He aſſiſts his Brother and the whole partie ſo much the more vigorously, as he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued there was more need, and euen thought aſſuredly, that it would be more easie for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19849:33"/>
him now to make an aduantageous gaine thereby, then in the life time of the ſaid Duke. Becauſe that the whole faction ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more need of him, he could more eaſily reduce them to his owne will. In ſo much as he aduanced the buſineſſe so for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>France</hi> eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped not his hands, but by miracle. And if he had beene content onely to diſſipate it, in ſtead of getting it intirely, he had therein obtain'd his ends. And this is the onely fault that he committed againſt his intereſt in this Affaire. For had he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the affection this <hi>Nation</hi> beares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her <hi>Kings,</hi> the deteſtation shee has of the <hi>Spanish</hi> dominion, beſides her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſickleneſſe, as alſo the reputation of the <hi>clemencie</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> IIII. he would not haue beene ſo obſtinate as to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſurmount things impoſſible, and would haue contented himſelfe to part the Realme among ſeuerall perſonnes. And aftewards vpon the differences that are wont to happen betweene <hi>vſurpers,</hi> it would haue beene farre more eaſie for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19849:33"/>
him to gett by peece-meale, what he would haue carried all at once. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it would haue beene a gaine great enough to him, to <hi>diuide</hi> this mightie <hi>Kingdome,</hi> the which being <hi>Vnited,</hi> does euery where impeach the amplification of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:19849:34"/>
               <head>THE SECOND DISCOVRSE VPON THE WARRE OF SAVOY.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſeemed that the Peace of <hi>Veruins</hi> had reſtabished a ſolid tranquillitie to <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> and that theſe two mightie Powers of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> wearied of troubling each other, had beene glad to taſt of reſt. But as it is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that in all accords which are made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Soueraigne States,</hi> there men leaue vndecided the <hi>Claimes</hi> about Which they cannot agree: So likewiſe in this Peace, the reſtitution of the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluces</hi> was remitted to another ſeaſon, in ſuch wiſe as <hi>Henry,</hi> afther hauing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed ſome yeares to ſetle againe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19849:34"/>
of his Realme in good order, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to queſtion the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> for the inuaſion of the ſaid Marquiſate, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he made him plainly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that he would haue it reſtored. This peece (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though little) is of very great importance. It is the Port of <hi>Italie</hi> whereby the <hi>French</hi> might paſſe, either to aſſault, or ſuccour it. Thoſe that feared their power, had reaſon to withſtand the deſigne of <hi>Henry,</hi> but thoſe that feared any other, fauoured <hi>him.</hi> So the intereſts of <hi>Italie</hi> were diuided. <hi>Emanuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> (as the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſsed of all in the buſineſſe) vſes all meanes to diuert this Tempeſt. He ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> not to forſake him, and gaineth the <hi>Popes</hi> Nephew, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Aldobrandin,</hi> to procure the <hi>Popes</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. But being exceedingly confident of his dexteritie and adreſse, he reſolued to goe into <hi>France,</hi> to the end that vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of treating this affaire, he might gaine ſome of the principall Miniſters of <hi>Henry,</hi> and raiſe a broile within the Kingdome,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19849:35"/>
herein he was at great coſt, and vſed ſuch sleights, that he failed but very little of his purpoſe. Neuertheleſse being too confident of a thing vncertaine, and hauing too much neglected the meanes of his true aſſurance, he became ſo ſurpriſed, that within three Moneths he was diſpoyled of all <hi>Breſse</hi> and <hi>Sauoy.</hi> This rude beginning awak'd him. He continues his practiſes in <hi>France,</hi> he haſteth the ſuccour of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and ſeekes the interceſſion of the <hi>Pope,</hi> who to this effect sendeth the Cardinall <hi>Aldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandin</hi> towards <hi>Henry</hi> for to treate the ſame. In the meane while euery one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, ſome to aſſault <hi>Piemont,</hi> others to defend it. but the mediation of the Peace was the ſtrongeſt. For it was concluded in the yeare 1600. wherein <hi>Sauoy</hi> was ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to the Duke, and <hi>Breſſe</hi> remained to <hi>Henry</hi> for exchange of the Marquisdome of <hi>Saluces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which made <hi>Henry</hi> commit this errour againſt his intereſt, was the deſire he had to taſt of repoſe, it being a thing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19849:35"/>
certaine that a man ordinarily flatters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in that whereunto his fancie carries him. This Prince naturally loued his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and the neceſſitie of his affaires all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies engaged him to labour; So as now ſeeing himſelfe at peace in his Relme, and beleeuing he had done enough for his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, he choſe rather to take a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for the ſaid Marquiſate, then to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barke himſelfe in a long warre.</p>
               <p>This Peace touched <hi>Ferdinand</hi> great Duke of <hi>Tuſcanie</hi> ſo much to the heart, (for the prejudice that it brought to the libertie of the Princes of the <hi>Italie</hi>) that he offered to breake it, by the meanes of 200000. crownes, wherewith He and the States of <hi>Venice</hi> should furnish the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Aldobrandin.</hi> But <hi>Henry</hi> would not hearken to it.</p>
               <p>In this affaire, and the ſequele thereof, there are two things remarkable. <hi>Viz.</hi> The loſſe which <hi>France</hi> hath ſuſtained by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluces:</hi> and the aduantage that one gets by gaining the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19849:36"/>
Nephewes of the <hi>Pope.</hi> By the <hi>firſt,</hi> the <hi>French-man</hi> has loſt all credit in the affaires of <hi>Italie,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> remaines <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> there, hauing noe more to contradict him. And by the <hi>ſecond,</hi> as it is a thing well knowne that the approbation of the <hi>Pope</hi> (on the <hi>Catholike</hi> partie) is of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: So likewiſe is it certaine, that to acquire the ſame, one muſt gaine <hi>his</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes, who cannot be wonne but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and reall benefits. For the eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their houſe being founded vpon the life of their <hi>Vnkle,</hi> who is commonly old, they will not waſt the time in vaine. So as he that does moſt readily gratifie them, carries them on his ſide.</p>
               <p>Whence I conclude, that the true intereſt of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is, to hinder the entrance of the <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Italie,</hi> to the end that he haue not there any oppoſition.</p>
               <p>The true intereſt of the <hi>French-man</hi> is to haue <hi>there</hi> one Port open, thereby to maintaine his reputation, and to share in the affaires, with the <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19849:36"/>And the true intereſt of the <hi>Italians</hi> is, throughly to expell all Strangers out of <hi>Italie,</hi> but not being able to doe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, their intereſt is, to conſerue their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie by the counterpoiſe of theſe two Powers, of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19849:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE THIRD DISCOVRSE</hi> VPON THE DIFFERENCE that happened betvveen Pope Paul V. and the Republike of Venice, the yeare <hi>1605.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſeemes eleuated to that high point of Majeſtie, wherein wee behold it at this preſent, it is certaine that it had deſignes proportioned to its greatneſse, which haue appear'd ſometimes more, ſometimes leſſe, according to the Nature of thoſe who enjoyed the <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> For thoſe <hi>Popes</hi> that were endued with ſufficient wiſedome to ſuſtaine the weight of ſuch a greatneſſe, haue allwaies much indeauoured to make ſome progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:19849:37"/>
for to approach this marke. But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they haue ſo cunninghy diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled theit enterpriſe, that from thence there is not arriued any ſcandall vnto <hi>Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendome,</hi> nor any dishonour to the <hi>Church:</hi> Some others thruſt on by an inconſiderate zeale, or inflamed with a deſire to get themſelues a name to poſteritie, or elſe hurried by the violence of their paſsions, are come ſo farre therein as to diſcouer this myſterie of the <hi>Romane Hierarchie,</hi> which by all reaſon of prudence and wiſe gouernment should not haue beene reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, till after it were accomplish'd.</p>
               <p>Of the number of theſe laſt was Pope <hi>Paul V.</hi> who euen from the beginning of his <hi>Papacie,</hi> blaming the moderation of his Predeceſſours, reſolu'd himſelfe to take a contrarie courſe, and to doe that (during his life, and out of ſeaſon) which could not be brought to an end in many ages, nor by a long ſucceſsion of fauorable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
               <p>But for as much as our intenſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine liueleſse, when they haue an object
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19849:38"/>
whereunto they cannot attaine. <hi>Paul</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that he should not haue to deale with <hi>Kings</hi> ſo eaſily as with <hi>Common-wealthes,</hi> (which being gouerned as by priuate perſonnes, ſeeme to haue leſſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, becauſe they haue leſſe luſter,) he determin'd for this effect to beginne by them. He quarelled firſt of all thoſe of <hi>Luca</hi> and <hi>Genoa,</hi> and made them obey, either by triumphing vpon their weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or by intereſſing himſelfe in the differences of particular perſonnes, who had receiued, or hoped to receiue ſome aduancement by the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> But not being content with this, he would ſet vpon the <hi>Republike</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> concerning whom the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> makes shew, not to haue had (for certaine time) the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction from thence, which shee did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, for two principall reaſons. The <hi>firſt</hi> becauſe shee excluded all Eccleſiaſticall perſonnes from the participation of her gouernment. The <hi>ſecond</hi> becauſe shee gaue not any penſion to the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19849:38"/>The <hi>Pope</hi> was diligent to find a plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ground to make this <hi>Common wealth</hi> feele the effects of his indignation, when in the yeare 1605. There was preſented ſuch an occaſion as he deſired.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Abbot,</hi> and a <hi>Canon</hi> (after many ſcandalls committed) were accuſed of hainous crimes, and brought to <hi>Venice,</hi> where they were impriſonned.</p>
               <p>Much about the ſame time there, the <hi>Republike</hi> renewed two ancient Lawes, for to make the ſame obſerued in all places of her dominion. <hi>The one forbidding that any e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cular goods should be alienated to Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall perſonnes: The other, whereby it was prohibited to build any Church without the permiſsion of the Senate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> became offended thereat, and ſaid: <hi>he might not endure that Eccleſiaſticall men should be iudged by ſecular Authoritie, for any crime whatſoeuer, and that it belonged to him alone to condemne, or abſolue them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it should ſeeme good vnto him.</hi> As for the two Lawes, he ſaid: <hi>they could not ſubſiſt, being contrarie to the Councells
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19849:39"/>
and Imperiall Conſtitutions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> after mature deliberation vpon the matter (hauing weighed on the one ſide the indignation of the Pope, and on the other ſide the Common libertie) answered; <hi>That they might not deliuer the Church-men iuſtly impriſoned: nor abolish the Lawes iuſtly eſtablished, without preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the libertie which God had giuen them, and which they had maintained for ſo many ages, by the blood of their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours That their State hauing proſpered by such Lawes, they thought they could not change them without incurring an euerlaſting brand of infamie to all poſtcritie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> growes more and more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, and takes a firme reſolution to make them obey. The <hi>Venetians</hi> endeauour by all manner of meanes to order the matter handſomely. They alleadge their reaſons with more then ordinarie ſubmiſſions, they ſend an extraordinarie Embaſſadour to <hi>Rome,</hi> that by this demonſtration of a reuerent regard, they might take from the <hi>Pope</hi> the opinion (which he had conceiued)
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19849:39"/>
that he was neglected, and alſo thereby giue him a faire pretext to retire himſelfe from the precipice where he lay. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the <hi>Pope's</hi> Briefs (which were ſo many thunder-ſtroakes againſt them) with all honour and reſpect. They humbly shew the deſire they had to content the <hi>Pope</hi> if it were poſſible without doing wrong to the common intereſt of all Princes, and to the fundamentall lawes of their gouernment, which binds them to take notice of the buildings that are erected within their Townes, to the end that from thence ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue nothing dammageable to the publike good. As for the alienation of <hi>Church-goods,</hi> they cannot permit the ſame without wholly ruining the forces of their State.</p>
               <p>As for the impunitie of Eccleſiaſticall perſonnes, they ſay: That in permitting the ſame, they should not onely derogate from their Soueraigntie, and the power they hold immediately from GOD, but alſo intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in the State examples of dangerous conſequence.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> anſwers: That he regards not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19849:40"/>
their Lawes whether old or new: and that it appertained to him, to change them at his pleaſure. That he would not allow any treating of the buſineſſe, but an abſolute obedience.</p>
               <p>In the meane while, he goes about to nullifie the election of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> becauſe it had beene made ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this <hi>difference,</hi> And whilſt that he proceeds in this ſort, the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> giues him part of his Election, with the accuſtomed <hi>reuerence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> (to make knowne the Iuſtice of their cauſe) doe conſult this aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aire by perſonnes well vers'd in ſuch matt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and therein they demaund the aduice of the moſt famous Doctors of <hi>Europe:</hi> They punctually relate the <hi>Controuerſie</hi> to all the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> their allies; And to the end that their right might appeare euen to poſteritie, they deliuer their answer to the <hi>Pope,</hi> becauſe that if the difference were reconciled, all the world might know that they were juſtified. The ſame is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they neuer called home their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19849:40"/>
before the <hi>Pope</hi> had retired his Nuntio. For although the Extraordinarie went backe to teſtifie ſome reſſentment after the receiuing of so many diſtaſtes: the Ordinarie neuertheleſſe continued there, to shew that they had allwaies an eare open to agreement. Laſtly when they could no longer hold from breaking off, they take a reſolution to defend their libertie, with ſuch an vnanimous conſent, that in the whole <hi>Senate</hi> there was not one voice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. Thereby fruſtrating the hopes which the <hi>Pope</hi> had of diſuniting them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> had promis'd him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> tooke a cleane contrary byas, for (men beleeu'd) he cared not a jot whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he went vpon good, or ill grounds. He imparted not this buſineſſe to other Princes till very late, neither did he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the aduiſe euen of the Cardinalls, but for fashion's ſake.</p>
               <p>Here is that which paſſed before the breach betwixt the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Venetians,</hi> wherein the <hi>Venetians</hi> exactly followed that which belonged to their intereſt. For
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19849:41"/>
their <hi>State</hi> being founded rather by Peace, then by Warre, and being more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for Counſell then for Armes, they ought euer dexterously to auoid any rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>During the time of the breach, the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> ſurmounted euen their owne ſelues, hauing giuen in this affaire a perpetuall example of perfect conduct. shewing as much conſtancie and courage in their reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of the injurie which they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded was done them: as before they had shewed ſubmiſſion to preuent the ſame. They euer answered thoſe who ſpake to them of agreement: <hi>That the remedie ought to be applied to the part whence the diſeaſe proceeded: That the Pope had receiued a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie diſpleaſure, the remedie whereof was a voluntary repentance.</hi> This notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they rejected not any propoſition, but much inſiſted vpon this point: <hi>That they had done onely what they ought: That the Pope in withdrawing his Nuntio had barr'd the way to agreement: That it belonged to him to make good againe, what he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19849:41"/>
had ſpoyled: and That when he shall haue taken off his pretended cenſures, they will not ſeeme eſtranged from Peace.</hi> But that which had beene moſt remarkable here was, that they were not a whit moued for all this tempeſt, prouiding with ſo much prudence, (both within and without their State) all that was neceſſarie to ſuſtaine ſuch a shock, that noe alteration at all was perceiued. The people remained in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: the Townes of their Dominion offered their meanes and forces: the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> obeyed without conſtraint: there was not shed one drop of blood.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope,</hi> in ſtead of shewing conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in his reſolution, beganne to relent ſo ſoone as had wrought his indignation by the interdict, leauing to be vnderſtood vnder-hand, that he would lend an eare to agreement, prouided that he might ſaue his credit. But when he ſaw the inflexible ſtedfaſtneſse of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> he reſolued to haue recourſe to force, and to intereſt the Catholike Princes in the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>France</hi> had noe other ſcope in this aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aire
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19849:42"/>
then to arbitrate the difference, and to haue the honour of deciding ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a queſtion between two Princes ſo conſiderable in Chriſtendome. For this effect shee shewed not any partialitie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be true that <hi>Villeroy</hi> (through his ambition to riſe to a <hi>Cardinalship</hi>) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined at firſt to the <hi>Pope's</hi> ſide, ſeruing his turne therein by the miniſtration of his ſonne, then Ambaſſadour at <hi>Rome.</hi> But ſeeing himſelfe disappointed of his hope, he returned to the temper which a juſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour ought to haue. So it is, that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a priuate intereſt does prejudice the publike. <hi>Happie are the States, wherein thoſe that ſit at the helme of gouernment, haue ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a ſpirit as not to ayme at any other greatneſſe then that which is inſeparably conioint with the glorie of the Prince whom they ſerue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> conceiued it beſt to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the diſcord betweene the two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, thinking that is was in their power to hinder the warre, if their profit ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: or elſe to make it ſerue their owne aduantage. They therefore let the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19849:42"/>
runne its courſe without preſcribing any thing to their Ambaſſadour which was at Rome. who handſomely intertained the Pope in his opinion, with intent to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a Cardinalship for his Brother by this meanes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Emperour</hi> was a Mediatour; the King of <hi>Poland</hi> fauoured the Republike: the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germanie</hi> medled not all in the matter.</p>
               <p>The <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> was glad to ſee this buſineſſe dayly waxe hot. He promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all aſſiſtance to the <hi>Republike</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> as by all reaſon he was obliged to deale in this manner. For he beleeued that this would rowſe vp the other <hi>Catholike Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> which were intereſsed to maintaine their <hi>Lawes.</hi> And that it would be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to deliberate of a <hi>Councell</hi> which may determine ſo many Controuerſies.</p>
               <p>The <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>vnited-Prouinces</hi> off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered to the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſuccour of armes and munition.</p>
               <p>The Princes of <hi>Italie,</hi> ſince they ſaw the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19849:43"/>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> remaine confuſed and wauering in himſelfe, as if he had manifeſtly repented, they appeare all newters in this affaire, foll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that which belonged to their true intereſt.</p>
               <p>Onely the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> let himſelfe be tranſported by his paſſion. For the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publike hauing written to his children with the title of Excellence, as shee had accuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omed to doe, He in deſpite kept Chappell without admitting there the Ambaſsadour of Venice, and this at the inſtance of the Nuntio reſiding neere vnto him. It is not in this affaire alone, that this Prince has carried himſelfe rather capriciously, then after the true Maxime of his <hi>intereſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>France</hi> continued to ſolicite the Accord, without shewing any paſsion for the one partie, or the other, following herein her true <hi>intereſt.</hi> For becauſe one shall hardly ſee an open warre betwixt two ſo paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique Princes, Shee could not reape any other profit by this Difference, then the honour onely to haue reconciled the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:19849:43"/>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> perceiuing this, beganne to recoile, and deſire to haue a hand in making <hi>peace,</hi> ſince they could not haue it in <hi>warre,</hi> They judged well that the <hi>Pope</hi> was diſpoſed to caſt himſelfe into their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and to goe which way they would, becauſe he had a mind to agreement. But they ſaw alſo the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſo firme in their reſolution, as they had noe hope to bend them. Wherefore they eſsayed to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them with the <hi>Turk,</hi> to the end they might be conſtrained to haue recourſe vnto them, and that by this meanes it should be in their power, to bring the Senate to accept ſuch conditions as the <hi>Pope</hi> pleaſed to allow them. But they failed ſo much in that which they endeauour'd to doe by the meanes of the <hi>Turk,</hi> as (on the contrary) it became aduantageous to the <hi>Republike.</hi> For though the Marqueſse <hi>de Saint-Croy</hi> hauing ranſacked <hi>Duras,</hi> beleeued that the <hi>Turks</hi> (to take reuenge) would turne againſt the <hi>Republike,</hi> as being neereſt, or at leaſt enter within the <hi>Gulfe.</hi> Yet it happened
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19849:44"/>
that the <hi>Turk</hi> perceiuing the <hi>Spanish</hi> wiles, commaunded the Admirall of his Fleet to aide the <hi>Venetians</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Spainards.</hi> But the <hi>Republike</hi> judging it not fit to make vſe of ſuch a helpe, (for feare the remedie should be worſe then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe it selfe,) shee put it off ſo handſomely that the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> receiued not any diſtaſt thereby. Neuertheleſſe making the <hi>Pope</hi> vnderſtand, that in caſe of neceſſitie, shee well knew whither to haue recourſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> out of ſeaſon offer'd a whole entire Armie to the <hi>Pope,</hi> Some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that it was for to reclaime the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> by this way, but it was nothing leſſe. For all whatſoeuer the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did then for the <hi>Pope,</hi> proceeded onely becauſe the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> was tickled with vaine-glorie, for that the <hi>Pope</hi> in his Briefs had giuen him the title of <hi>Excellence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly they perceiued in <hi>Spaine</hi> that this buſineſse would be ended by treatie, and that <hi>France,</hi> was to haue all the honour thereof. This made them about to ſend
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19849:44"/>
extraordinaire Embaſſadours from one ſide to the other, but it was too late, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gociation being ſo farre aduanced by the <hi>French,</hi> that twas impoſſible to get it out of their hands. Inſomuch as whatſoeuer the <hi>Spaniards</hi> could doe to croſſe the Treatie, the honour thereof remained full and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Henry,</hi> who ended the buſineſse by the dexteritie and prudence of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>de Ioyeuſe,</hi> and of <hi>Frenes-Canaye,</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie Embaſſadour at <hi>Venice.</hi> The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonners were deliuered into the hands of the Embaſſadour: The Lawes of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publike</hi> continued without alteration: and the <hi>Pope</hi> was forced to take off the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict without any token of ſubmiſsion from the ſaid <hi>Republike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This has beene a warre of Negociation, wherein the <hi>Venetians</hi> full and wholly carried the victorie. Likewiſe one muſt acknowledge, they were ingaged to deale in that part wherein they were moſt able.</p>
               <p>They followed therein all the max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19849:45"/>
of their true intereſt: The <hi>Pope</hi> did quite contrary: <hi>Spaine</hi> was amuſing after Chymeraes: and <hi>France</hi> had the ſcope which shee ought to haue, wherefore shee likewiſe had the glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19849:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FOVRTH DISCOVRSE CONCERNING</hi> the Truce of the Low Countries vvith the King of Spaine.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Truce of the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> is an infallible proofe of the excellence of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in matter of Negociation.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſeeing that in fortie yeares Space, the warre had augmented and enriched this <hi>State,</hi> in ſtead of ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and that it would greatly diminish his reputation to treate of Peace with thoſe, whom (euen till then) he had treated as Rebells, he therefore reſolued to doe his vtmoſt to enter into their Country, and to make them feele (euen within their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes) the diſcommoditie of Warre. For which purpoſe, he employed the two laſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19849:46"/>
Summers vnder the commaund of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> one of the renownedſt Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the time, Who with powerfull Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies endeauoured to enter, the firſt yeare into <hi>Frisland,</hi> and the ſecond into <hi>Holland.</hi> Neuertheleſſe <hi>Maurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (a Captaine to whom wee owe the reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the auncient militarie diſcipline) all though he was much inferiour to the forces of <hi>Spinola,</hi> yet he made ſo good vſe of the ſituation of his Country, that he fruſtrated all his endeauours. This hauing depriued the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> of all hope to conquer by force, he reſolued at laſt to make triall of a Treatie, at the coſt euen of his reputation. But his end herein was, 1. to ſecure the trafficke of the <hi>Indies:</hi> where he was endammaged by them, 2. to diuide them in the time of peace: and laſtly to beare armes more aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageously againſt people leſſe trained in warre, and more eaſie to ſubdue being confident that any good ſucceſſe in ſome affaire would make him recouer that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation which he then hazarded, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19849:46"/>
whereof he has beene euer jealous. A <hi>Monke</hi> did firſt lay open the matter to a <hi>Holland</hi> Marchant. The hope giuen to the <hi>States</hi> that in this Accord, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> would acknowledge them for <hi>free States,</hi> made them giue eare, whereupon followed a ſuſpenſion of Armes for to treate more at large.</p>
               <p>This intermiſſion awaked the intereſſed and neighbour Princes. <hi>Henry's</hi> mind was troubled with the true interereſt of his Eſtate, which he beſt of all knew, and alſo by his particular affections. The <hi>States</hi> (by reaſon of their intereſt) had ſuccoured him in his neceſſitie: He (for the ſame reaſon) powerfully aſſiſted them in his proſperitie. He willingly would haue them continue The warre, prouided that he augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted not his aſſiſtance: They offered to continue the ſame, on co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition that he would double the money which he gaue them yearely. The deſire of doing thriftily, made him ſeeme to incline, and not alltogether aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don his true intereſt, thinking it should be a great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for him to remoue from his frontiers
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19849:47"/>
ſuch good Armes which a Peace or long Truce might diſſipate, and that it should be a great honour for him to cauſe the Low Countries to be declared a free State, Inſomuch as He bent his thoughts to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Arbitratour of this negociation, and to make it ſucceed aduantageously for the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IAMES the firſt, King of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe ſtrong inclination to peace did not alſo permit him to follow the true intereſt of his Realme, which was to nourish Warre in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> for to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the forces of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and hinder their entrepriſe vpon him, he contents himſelfe to haue part in the Treatie by his Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours.</p>
               <p>Diuers Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germanie</hi> (imagining well that the Armes of <hi>Spaine</hi> being no more imployed there, might fall vpon them) doe likewiſe ſend their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, of purpoſe to diuert this Accord, os elſe to procure the protection of thoſe that intermedled in the buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maurice</hi> whoſe particular intereſt was
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19849:47"/>
joyned with the true intereſt of the <hi>States,</hi> wholly withſtood the Accord. <hi>Bernaueld</hi> who had moſt abilitie in the State-affaires of the Country, ſeeing that his owe credit grew in Peace rather then in Warre, he would haue the intereſts of the <hi>State</hi> to ſerue his owne ends. Here is the true pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait of thoſe that dealed in this affaire.</p>
               <p>But for the better vnderſtanding of the true intereſt of the <hi>States,</hi> we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount higher, and come to the originall. <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who alone in this Age had the honour to found a State, (although neither his disgraces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, nor the endeauours of <hi>Philip,</hi> the moſt puiſſant and able Prince of his Time, could haue hindred him,) was conſtrained to aſſemble the peeces for to compoſe a bodie thereof, with ſuch conditions as each Towne and Prouince required. For, hauing met with people that haue euer affected their libertie more then their very liues, he could not alter the conditions whereupon they firſt joyned themſelues vnto him. This ſame hath cauſed in this <hi>State</hi> ſo many
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19849:48"/>
Republikes as there be Townes, amongſt whom (in a generall decree) pluralitie of voices has noe place, becauſe that if any one Towne approue it not, shee is not bound to obſerue it. So as he deuiſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to flatter them in their libertie, that he might wholly take off their deſire to complie with <hi>Philip,</hi> then to propound vnto them good Lawes, for to maintaine them in the time of Peace.</p>
               <p>His ſonne <hi>Maurice,</hi> brought vp from his infancie in Armes, thought principally of the eſtablishing of militarie diſcipline, as the thing then moſt neceſſarie to vphold the <hi>State,</hi> wherein he ſurpaſſed all the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of his time. Inſomuch as this <hi>State</hi> beeing exceeding well grounded for to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt by warre, and as ill to maintaine it selfe in Peace, it is euident, that the true intereſt thereof is to continue the Warre.</p>
               <p>According to the intereſt of each Prince, their Ambaſſadours being aſſembled at the <hi>Hague,</hi> did worke about. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> make a great difficultie to ratifie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the <hi>Archdukes,</hi> (who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19849:48"/>
the <hi>States</hi> free, and ſoueraigne) to the intent to make them better relish the ſame, and that in yeelding they might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of them, conditions that would worke their ruine. As, the graunt of libertie of conſcience to <hi>Catholikes,</hi> thereby to make diuiſions among them: The priuation of trafficke in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and ſo to make a mutinie by the Marchands, the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable corporation amongſt them: Beſides the exchange of certaine places moſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and moſt prejudiciall to the ſaid <hi>States.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maurice</hi> earneſtly oppoſed ſuch condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>Bernaueld</hi> durſt not countenance them. <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> (perceiuing the venome hidden vnder the ſame) could not digeſt them. In ſuch wiſe as all Treatie of peace being broken, they renew that of a Truce for many yeares: <hi>Maurice</hi> doth his beſt to hinder it, but <hi>Bernaueld</hi> backed by <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> is the cauſe they did hearken to it. The worke beginnes anew, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſeeing they could not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19849:49"/>
obtaine the conditions which they deſired, imagining alſo their repoſe to be very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, at length they gaue ouer, ſauing that the Article, wich declared the <hi>States free,</hi> and that of trafficke in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> were couched ſo obſcurely, as they might ſaue their reputation, and interpret them to their owne aduantage, as occaſion should ſerue.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, the <hi>French</hi> for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the <hi>States</hi> to conclude, make a league with them, wherein they oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to giue them pay for tenne thouſand Souldiers. Specially for to make them keepe the Truce, in caſe it should be broken on the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſide, whereupon the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> complaining, they were answered, that whatſoeuer was done, was for their good, and that without doing the ſame, nothing could be obtained. <hi>Maurice</hi> for his part yeelds vnto that which he could not hinder, conditionally that the Armie might be maintained for the ſecuritie of the State, <hi>Henry</hi> approueth this condition,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19849:49"/>
and contributeth to the maintenance of 4000 Foote, and 200. Horſe. So as, the Truce was concluded for twelue yeares: the <hi>States</hi> acknowledged <hi>free and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:</hi> and their Ambaſſadours receiued in this qualitie by Princes. Thus ended this negociation which laſted two yeares, where each one endeauours to deceiue the other, and alſo flatters himſelfe with the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of hauing gotten that which he had deſired.</p>
               <p>In effect, <hi>Henry</hi> had the moſt honour in this affaire, and the <hi>States</hi> (by his meanes) the moſt profit. But he being dead, and <hi>Louys</hi> vpon the Throne at nine yeares of age, there was an vniuerſall alteration in <hi>France.</hi> For, <hi>Marie</hi> had obtain'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie, and willing to ſtrengthen her au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie againſt the Princes of the blood, and great ones of the Realme, shee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a diſunion amongſt them, and caſt herſelfe into the armes of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> beleeuing that shee had then need of the former Power, and allwaies of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19849:50"/>
inſomuch as during the time of her gouernment, the true intereſt of <hi>France</hi> being abandonned, there was taken the contrarie courſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> loſt not ſo good an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, eſpecially vpon the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> in the buſineſſe of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> the which <hi>Bernaueld</hi> (ſeeing himſelfe vpheld by <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> through the practiſes of <hi>Spaine</hi>) vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to maintaine againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in ſuch wiſe as that from a diſpute of Religion, there was made an affaire of State, ſo pernicious, that it was like to rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne this Commonweath. Here it was where the <hi>Spaniard</hi> diſplayed all his cunning, for to make <hi>Marie</hi> worke in this Country ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his intereſts. He perſwaded her that her disunion was aduantageous to her to maintaine her authoritie. To the end that shee might not aſſiſt the Princes of the blood diſontented with her, nor the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>France</hi> which might joyne with the ſaid Princes. He makes her to act a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious zeale, which is an euill coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19849:50"/>
to thoſe that entertaine it. So as the Ambaſſadours of <hi>France</hi>) vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of zeale to Religion) become ſollicitours of the affaires of <hi>Spaine</hi> in <hi>Holland.</hi> They fauour the cauſe of <hi>Bernaueld:</hi> they foment the diuiſion within the State: they bring it vpon the very brinke of its downefall, and had it not beene for the patience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courage of <hi>Maurice,</hi> aſſiſted by the ſouldiers, this Republike had runne the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to ſeeme as ſonne extinct, as borne.</p>
               <p>By that which is aforeſaid, and by the ſequele of affaires, one may judge that the true intereſts of the State of the <hi>vnited Prouinces</hi> are to maintaine warre againſt <hi>Spaine,</hi> otherwiſe it would be ruined of it ſelfe. The intereſts of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> are to aſſiſt the ſaid State, for to giue <hi>Spaine</hi> this bone to picke. The intereſts of the <hi>Germane</hi> Princes are to foment the ſame, to the end that by the fall of this burden, they likewiſe be not ouerthrowne. And the intereſts of <hi>Spaine</hi> are to keepe all the other in broiles amongſt themſelues, or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19849:51"/>
elſe ſet them one againſt another, leaſt they should all accord againſt her. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo ſoone as any of them haue aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donned theſe maximes, their affaires fall to the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:19849:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FIFTH DISCOVRSE VPON THE</hi> affaire about the ſucceſsion of <hi>Cleues</hi> and <hi>Iulliers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, <hi>Germanie</hi> liued very happie, ſo long as shee kept her true intereſt, and whil'ſt that the <hi>Emperour</hi> did containe himſelfe within the bounds of the lawes of the <hi>Empire,</hi> which ballancing the power thereof with that of the Princes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publikes of <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſuffered them not to vſurpe one vpon another.</p>
               <p>The firſt that forſooke this intereſt were the <hi>Princes Electors,</hi> in hauing continued the Imperial dignitie without interruption to many of one and the ſame familie, who in tract of time haue raiſed the ſame to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19849:52"/>
the prejudice of the Imperiall Lawes, the which hath chiefly happened to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſpecially ſince this houſe and that of <hi>Spaine</hi> haue beene both the ſelfe ſame thing. For, ſeeing her ſelfe eſtablished in ſo high a dignitie, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſuch a Power, shee was willing to be there perpetuated, and becauſe shee would not be violently incountred here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, shee has eſsayed to put downe thoſe who had lawfull right to interrupt that courſe, endeauoring likewiſe to lift vp her ſelfe by abolishing the lawes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and by vſurping the principall States, and Townes thereof.</p>
               <p>The firſt euident occaſion that has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in our time this deſigne, was vpon the ſucceſſion of <hi>Cleues</hi> and <hi>Iulliers,</hi> which happened in the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> the yeare 1609. occaſioned by the death of <hi>Iohn William,</hi> who hauing noe children of his owne, left this goodly heritage to his foure ſiſters married, to the Elector of <hi>Brandebourg:</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Neubourg:</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Deu ponts:</hi> and to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſse
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19849:52"/>
of <hi>Turgaw.</hi> The firſt of theſe laied claime to the ſucceſsion entire, as indiuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hauing married the eldeſt. The ſecond makes the ſame claime, becauſe the eldeſt ſiſter died before the brother, and his wife was the eldeſt of the ſiſters liuing. The two other ſay that it ought to be equally parted betwixt them all foure. Moreouer the Electour of <hi>Saxonie</hi> reuiued an old title, and alſo the Duke of <hi>Neuers</hi> another. <hi>Brandebourg</hi> and <hi>Neubourg</hi> enter in poſſeſſion, the Emperour becomes off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended thereat, pretending that the whole heritage ought to be ſequeſtred into his hands, and each of them to vndergoe his ordinance. He ſends thither <hi>Leopold</hi> a Prince of hie owne Houſe, who ſeiſeth on <hi>Iulliers</hi> the principall fortreſſe of the Country.</p>
               <p>The Princes that were in poſſeſſion, ſeeing ſuch an obſtacle, judged well that this ſequeſtration tended to an vſurpation, and not thinking themſelues able enough to reſiſt, in regard of the neighbourhood of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and of the beſt forces of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:19849:53"/>
(who in an occaſion ſo aduantageous for the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> would not faile to helpe her kinſeman) they haue recourſe to thoſe, who were principally intereſſed to impeach the amplification of the ſaid Houſe. They rallie to their defence, <hi>France, England,</hi> and the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> with the moſt part of the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germanie,</hi> who made ſuch a mightie warlike prouiſion to recouer <hi>Iulliers</hi> ſeiſed by the ſaid <hi>Leopold,</hi> that notwithſtanding the vnexpected death of <hi>Henry,</hi> which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened before the execution, yet the deſigne was happily accomplished, <hi>Spaine</hi> not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to oppoſe it.</p>
               <p>One may ſee in this affaire, euery one's true intereſt. That of the <hi>Emperour</hi> was, to make vſe of the occaſion to catch hold of ſuch an Eſtate in <hi>Germanie:</hi> That of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to aſſiſt him therein, as well for the principall end, which is, the aduancement of the whole Houſe, as for the neighbourhood of the ſaid State to <hi>Flanders:</hi> That of the lawfull ſucceſſours, was to maintaine their owne right: That
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19849:53"/>
of the <hi>Germaine</hi> Princes, not to ſuffer that Power whereof they were jealous, to be ſtrengthened by their owne weakening: And the intereſts of <hi>France, England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> were, not to permit the amplifying of all the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Hitherto euery one played his game aright; but <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> for to ſupport the intereſts of <hi>Spaine</hi> that promiſed her to maintaine hers euen to the end, abandonneth thoſe of <hi>France,</hi> and againe ſecondeth the trouble about this ſucceſsion.</p>
               <p>The occaſion was offred by the impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Princes that held the poſseſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which cauſed the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> to reattempt the buſineſſe. The ſonnes of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debourg</hi> and <hi>Newbourg</hi> did joyntly gouerne this faire Eſtate, The fortereſſes were guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by equall garriſons: they dwelt in the ſame Pallace, and managed their affaires with one common hand. But this laſted not long, it being no eaſie matter to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne a State long time after this manner without diſſenſion, eſpecially between two Princes of diuerſe houſes, where there is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19849:54"/>
alſo diuerſitie of Religion. They beganne to enter into jealouſie one of another. Thoſe that were friends to them both, and intereſſed in their ſubſiſtence, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſame and fearing leaſt their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligence should increaſe, perſwaded them to make an alliance together. <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> agrees thereto, goes to the Electour <hi>Brandebourg,</hi> and requires of him his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in marriage. But as the beſt meates being corrupted turne into the ſtrongeſt poiſon: ſo in the moſt wholeſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell giuen to theſe <hi>Princes</hi> to confirme their amitie, there was found occaſion of a moſt implacable hatred, which cauſed the ruine of them both in the ſaid ſucceſſion. For, whil'ſt they were in the deboshes of their feaſtes, the <hi>Electour</hi> vpon ſome diſcourſe that did not pleaſe him, offended <hi>Newbourg</hi> ſo farre (euen in his owne houſe, and at the table) as to giue him a boxe on the eare, for which he would not afterward make him any teaſonable ſatisfaction, In ſuch wiſe, that in ſtead of a wife, he carries backe an offence ſo engrauen in his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19849:54"/>
heart, as he admitteth noe other counſell but that of reuenge. This ſpirit thus exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated, being vpon returne to <hi>Cleue-land,</hi> it was eaſie for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to gaine him to them. They made meanes to marrie him with the ſiſter of the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> perſwaded him to turne <hi>Catholike,</hi> for to make all the <hi>Catholike</hi> league of <hi>Germanie</hi> to be on his ſide; they take him into pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and giue him a penſion,</p>
               <p>The <hi>vnited States</hi> ſeeing how preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall this change would be to them, they ſupported <hi>Brandebourg.</hi> Theſe Princes from ſuſpicions doe come to attempts, <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> ſeiſeth on <hi>Duſſeldorp: Brandebourg</hi> on <hi>Iulliers,</hi> from whence the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> takes a pretexte to ſtirre, and armeth pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully to recouer the ſame. The <hi>States</hi> on the other ſide, prepare to defend it. They furnish it with men and munition fitt to ſuſtaine a great ſiege. The true intereſts of <hi>France</hi> being forſaken, they had nothing from thence but words, and Embaſſages, <hi>England</hi> ſeeing <hi>France</hi> had giuen off, was
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19849:55"/>
contented to doe the like, in ſending her Embaſſadours. The Princes of <hi>Germanie</hi> ſeeing themſelues forſaken of theſe two Crownes, and diuided amongſt themſelues both by Religion, and by the different aff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ections that they bore to thoſe two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they therefore ſtirre not at all. <hi>Spaine</hi> finding now noe other oppoſition, but onely from the <hi>vnited States,</hi> proſecuteth her intentions, and whilſt shee amuſeth the Ambaſſadours of theſe two Kings, shee ſends <hi>Spinola</hi> into the country with a puiſsa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Armie, who in ſtead of ſetting vpon <hi>Iulliers,</hi> (which was then but a rude entrepriſe,) he goes to inuade the <hi>States,</hi> he paſſeth the <hi>Rhine,</hi> aſſaults and takes <hi>wezel</hi> within foure dayes.</p>
               <p>Maurice ſeeing this exploit, he delayes no longer, leaues the Ambaſſadours in their negociation, takes <hi>Rez</hi> and <hi>Emerik,</hi> and at length (a thing neuer before ſeene) theſe two Armies ſeize vpon this heritage without impeachment one of another: without brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Truce: and alſo without making
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19849:55"/>
any skirmish at all. For, when one of theſe Captaines had poſſeſſed a place, the other ſtill retired, not pretending any thing there. So as he that was moſt diligent, made the moſt progreſſion. The reaſon of this gentle dealing was, becauſe <hi>Spinola</hi> knew well the Armie of <hi>Maurice</hi> to be better then his owne, <hi>Maurice</hi> likewiſe well vnderſtood that the ſafeguard of the <hi>States</hi> conſiſted in the ſubſiſtence of his Armie. So as he beleeued he should come off with honour enough, to diuide this ſpoyle with the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> without expoſing any thing to danger.</p>
               <p>Is is now eaſie to judge that the ruine of the Princes which were in the poſſeſſion, proceeded from hence, viz. Becauſe that Newbourg forſaking his true intereſt to follow his paſſion, caſt himſelfe into the armes of <hi>Spaine:</hi> Becauſe the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germanie</hi> not conſidering their true intereſt, did not ſtirre at all: likewiſe becauſe <hi>France</hi> embracing not the intereſt of <hi>Maurice</hi> forſooke her owne, and for
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19849:56"/>
that <hi>England</hi> did the like with <hi>France.</hi> On the other ſide, the aduantage that <hi>Spaine</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> haue gotten in this conqueſt proceeded hence, for that both the one and the other were entirely fixed vpon their true intereſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:19849:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE SIXT DISCOVRSE VPON THE</hi> Election of the Count Palatine to the Kingdome of Bohemia.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the quantitie of ſet battailes, or the number of the perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes slaine: or the reuolution of ſundrie States: or the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the Princes intereſsed: or the length of the time might make a Warre memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, then that which <hi>Germanie</hi> now ſuffers, is in the higheſt degree, ſince that there are giuen already more then fifteene battailes: three hundred thouſand men haue loſt their liues in the ſame: almoſt all the States of <hi>Germanie</hi> haue thereby changed their condition and their Maſters: all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> haue taken an intereſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19849:57"/>
therein: and it is now fourteene yeares ſince the warre begunne, without being yet ended.</p>
               <p>The occaſion thereof happened through the rejection of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> from the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſaid Kingdome conferred on the perſonne of <hi>Frederic</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Rheine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> would eſtablish himſelfe in a dignitie, which he beleeued was vnjuſtly taken fron him: The <hi>ſecond</hi> would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine himſelfe in the Kingdome, as being juſtly choſen thereunto. The <hi>firſt</hi> would make it a busineſſe of Religion, thereby to intereſt all the Catholike Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> in the ſame: The <hi>ſecond</hi> would shew that it was nothing elſe but a State-warre, that he might intereſt in the ſame all thoſe by whom the greatneſſe of <hi>Spaine</hi> was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p>But for to judge well of this great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, one ought to remount a little higher. It is certaine that ſince the warre which happened about the ſucceſſion of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19849:57"/>
                  <hi>Cleues</hi> and <hi>Iulliers, Germanie</hi> was as it were deuided in two factions, and (in imitation of the Catholikes) the Proteſtants alſo had made a League, whereof the Prince Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Palatine</hi> was choſen Chiefe, as the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> had beene of the other. The pretence which euery one tooke for the defence of his Religion, did agrrauate the matter amongſt them. And the ſecure peace which this nation had enjoyed a long time, did not permir her (following the reuolution of this world) to abide thus any longer. There wanted onely an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make her bandie againſt her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bohemians</hi> preſent this occaſion, whether it were by reaſon of their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall fickleneſſe, or for being ill treated in the libertie of their conſciences, or elſe through ſome diſcontentment of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall men amongſt them, or for all theſe reaſons together, they reject <hi>Ferdinand</hi> their King, and chooſe <hi>Frederick</hi> in his place. And (for to render themſelues ſo much the more irreconcilable with him) in the full aſſembly of the States, they caſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19849:58"/>
thoſe of his partie out of the windowes.</p>
               <p>This action arriued in the yeare 1619. after which euery one tooke armes. The Proteſtants were the forwardeſt, for they were alreadie prepared to it, and attended onely the bruit of this Election to beginne the game. Amongſt thoſe who tooke part with <hi>Frederick,</hi> he that brought the moſt powerfull aſſiſtance, was <hi>Betheleem Gabor,</hi> who from an ordinarie Gentleman being made Prince of <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> and fearing the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which had alwaies endeauored to appropriate this State, he put himſelfe into the protection of the <hi>Turk</hi> for to ſecure the ſame, and finding ſo faire an opportunitie to depreſſe this Houſe, his intereſt ſuffered him not to looſe it. The <hi>vnited Prouinces</hi> (not to be wanting to their intereſt) doe here contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute on their part. The King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> for the ſame reaſon, and alſo for his honour and reputation, aſſiſteth his Nephew. King <hi>Iames</hi> more intereſſed then he, forgetteth his intereſt concerning his Sonne in law. The King of <hi>France</hi> likewiſe drawes backe,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19849:58"/>
and ſtands newter. At this beginning <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> is ill handled, and reduced to great extremities.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Spaine</hi> ſeeing that shee muſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her share to, or elſe looſe both her hopes and reputation, shee ſpares nothing, but vſeth all manner of meanes. In <hi>Germanie</hi> shee vrgeth the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> againſt the <hi>Palatine</hi> in point of honour, shee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates vnto him that he holds his Electorship of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and that he cannot maintaine it without her. At <hi>Rome</hi> shee perſwades the <hi>Pope</hi> that her loſſe is the ruine of the Catholike Religion, and the meanes to make all Chriſtendome a prey to the <hi>Turk,</hi> inſomuch as the <hi>Pope</hi> abandonning his true intereſt takes part with her, fournisheth both men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and laboureth to declare the other Catholike Princes for her defence. In <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> shee eaſily entertaines King <hi>Iames</hi> in his peaceable inclination. In <hi>France</hi> (by the Nuntio's helpe) shee gaineth the Duke <hi>de Luine,</hi> who hauing vſurped neere <hi>Loüys</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:19849:59"/>
the authoritie that <hi>Marie</hi> had there poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he tooke alſo the ſame maximes, ſupporting himſelfe by <hi>Spaine,</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faileth in ſuch occaſions to maintaine thoſe who diſtruſting their owne worth, ſeeke their ſecuritie out of the Realme. So as the intereſt of a Fauorite being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before that of the State, they aſſiſt <hi>Spaine.</hi> But to the end that it might be with more profit and leſſe noiſe, they vndertake an agreement: they ſend Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours to both parties: they amuſe the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> with faire hopes: they make them looſe the opportunitie of a victorie which they had in hand, and they induce them to diſarme. In the meane while the <hi>Catholikes</hi> hauing this time for reſpite, ſtrengthen themſelues on all ſides: take their aduantage: proſecute their former deſignes, and by gaining the battaile of <hi>Prague,</hi> wholly ruine their ennemies.</p>
               <p>In this reuolution of affaires, <hi>Spaine</hi> makes good vſe of the victorie, continues her intelligences amongſt her Neighbours,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19849:59"/>
that shee might not be diuerted in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and joynes her forces of <hi>Flanders</hi> to thoſe of <hi>Italie,</hi> for to become abſolute Miſtreſſe of the Empire. Feare and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion interpoſe amongſt the Princes of <hi>Germanie</hi> and the Imperiall Townes, Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one haſteth to ſubmit himſelfe to the yoake, diſtruſting leaſt he should not be time enough receiued there. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours of Princes, and Magiſtrates of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealthes are corrupted by money, and all contribute to forge the irons of their owne bondage.</p>
               <p>This kind of proceeding makes the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> feare leaſt the firing of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie</hi> conſume him, he takes the defence thereof, and goes into the field, but is van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished, looſeth part of his dominions, and for to recouer it againe, is conſtrained to make a dishonourable peace. The <hi>Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanian</hi> ſeeing this diſorder, maketh his peace likewiſe, but ſo much the better by reaſon of the <hi>Turk's</hi> protection.</p>
               <p>Here was the iſſue of the ſecond reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the affaires of <hi>Germanie,</hi> which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19849:60"/>
proceeded chiefely from this, that <hi>France</hi> proſtituted her intereſt to the greatneſſe of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee should come now to the third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution. <hi>It is oftentimes more difficult to gouerne ourſelues well in great proſperitie, then in aduerſitie, becauſe that the one ingenders neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and lulles vs in idleneſſe: but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie of the other keeps vs waking, and makes vs ſearch the meanes of our reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Such was the caſe of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> who ſeeing herſelfe from ſuch a heauie blow authoriſed beyond her hopes, abſolute Miſtreſſe of <hi>Germanie,</hi> of innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable armies entertained at the coſt of her ennemies, <hi>France</hi> not ſtirring againſt her proceedings, and beſides imbroiled in Ciuill warres. <hi>England</hi> yet forgetting her intereſt. <hi>Holland</hi> hauing enough to doe to conſerue her owne, and <hi>Italie</hi> without appearance of being able to defend it ſelfe, Shee therefore feareth nothing, but deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all, in ſuch wiſe as without hiding any more her deſigne vnder the pretence of Religion, (wherewith shee had ſo well
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19849:60"/>
ſerued her purpoſe euen to the preſent) shee openly inuades the Territories of the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> being a great Catholike, vaunting shee could not ſuffer a Prince that was <hi>French borne</hi> to poſſeſſe any State in <hi>Italie,</hi> which is the firſt remarkable errour that shee committed againſt her owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. For, this vſurpation gaue all the Princes of <hi>Italie</hi> to vnderſtand, that the tempeſt would come whirling vpon them, inſomuch as the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> was aſſiſted by the moſt reſolute amongſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Louys</hi> cannot digeſt this affront, and being aſſiſted with a Counſell whoſe pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and reſolution was neceſſarie in ſuch a perillous conjunction of affaires, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately imployed his Armes in his defence, Which was the firſt occaſion of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, wherein he recouered the vſage of his true intereſt. But ſeeing that diuerſions in <hi>Germanie</hi> were needfull for him, and not finding the ſame amongſt the <hi>Germains</hi> being oppreſſed with the burden of ſo grieuous a ſubjection, he goes to ſeeke
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19849:61"/>
them in the cold Northerne parts. The renowne of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Swede-land</hi> had beene carried euen vnto him. This Prince his deſire of glorie made him eaſily ſurmount any difficulties he could imagine, likewiſe his vaſt and great deſignes he ſurpaſſed as it were by ſuch a courage in execution, as made him not dishearken to any enterpriſe. The conqueſts of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein</hi> (Generall of the <hi>Emperour's</hi> armie) vpon the <hi>Balticke</hi> ſea, and the prouiſions which he made to render himſelfe Maſter there, made the King of <hi>Swede-land</hi> know, that he might well be in ſuſpicion of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and that his intereſt was to oppoſe the ſame. He therefore allieth himſelfe with <hi>France,</hi> and prepares to enter into <hi>Germanie,</hi> for to deliuer it from the thraldome whereunto it was reduced.</p>
               <p>Here is the ſecond fault that <hi>Spaine</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt her true intereſt, to wit, the contemning of this Prince. For whilſt that on the one ſide he enters into <hi>Germanie,</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> (at the ſollicitation of the King of <hi>Spaine</hi>) ſendeth his beſt troupes
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19849:61"/>
into <hi>Italie</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> which welmoſt all perished there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great effect. And the ſucceſſe of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> in <hi>Germanie</hi> was ſuch, as that thoſe of the <hi>Emperour's</hi> ſide and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> were faine to conclude a peace in <hi>Italie</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> (at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of what they had gotten, and of that reputation whereof they make ſo great eſteeme) for to draw back the remainder of their ſcattered troupes to the ſuccour of <hi>Germanie,</hi> leauing in the hand of the <hi>French, Cazal</hi> for a place of armes in <hi>Italie,</hi> and <hi>Pignerol</hi> as a port to enter therein. So as the deſire to conquer <hi>Italie</hi> before they were well aſſured of the conqueſt of <hi>Germanie,</hi> made them looſe both the one and the other.</p>
               <p>This happie exploite of <hi>Loüys,</hi> made him acknowledge his former errours, and wholly embrace his true intereſt. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuers the <hi>Grizons</hi> from their ſeruitude; diuerteth the vnited <hi>States</hi> from accepting a Truce, maintaineth the <hi>Swedish</hi> partie notwithſtanding the death of <hi>Guſtavus,</hi> 
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:19849:62"/>
defendeth the Electour of <hi>Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> againſt the perſecutions of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and chaſtiſeth the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> for adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the <hi>Emperour.</hi> In a word, he does brauely recouer his place, which his ill Counſellours had made him forgoe.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Vrb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> ſeeing himſelfe deliuered from the apprehenſion of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Germains,</hi> hauing likewiſe vnderſtood by the inuaſion made vpon the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> that they would deale noe oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erwiſe with the Catholike States, then with the Proteſtants, he thereupon oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them. The Republike of <hi>Venice</hi> that conſiders better then any other State what belongs to her true intereſt, and which neuer failes but in too much circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (as ordinarily thoſe Common weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes doe, which are not founded by Armes.) shee continueth neuertheleſſe her aſſiſtance to the Duke of <hi>Mantua. Amedis</hi> Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> receiuing inſtruction by the danger that he and his Father were in to looſe their Eſtates through neglecting their true intereſt, does now rejoyne himſelfe to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19849:62"/>
                  <hi>France.</hi> The other Princes of <hi>Italie</hi> ſeeing the aide of <hi>France</hi> could be noe impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them, let goe the apprehenſion which they had of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The <hi>Germane</hi> Princes and <hi>Imperiall</hi> Townes ſeeing themſelues ſupported by the armes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Swedeland,</hi> aſſiſted by the diuerſion of their other allies, and reaſſured by the proſperous ſucceſſe of their affaires, they take courage againe. <hi>England</hi> alone, as if shee were in another world, remaines without medling at all.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, <hi>Spaine</hi> failes not to animate her cauſe, takes vp againe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the <hi>Catholike</hi> Religion, which shee had as it were left off, and perceiuing the errour shee committed thereby, crieth more then euer againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> exceedingly vrgeth the <hi>Pope</hi> to haue of him his money, and his fulminations, maketh much of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> courteth the <hi>English,</hi> intertaineth diſſenſion in the houſe Royall of <hi>France,</hi> mightily endeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oureth to draw the <hi>vnited Prouinces</hi> to a Truce, laboureth to diſengage the Duke
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19849:63"/>
of <hi>Saxonie</hi> from the <hi>Swedish</hi> partie, neither is shee caſt off by any repulſe. And yet notwithſtanding shee ſpares neither men nor money for to raiſe new armies to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her ennemies. In briefe, neceſſitie has reduced euery one to follow his true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, which is the reaſon that in this laſt reuolution, the conteſtation about theſe affaires is of longer continuance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:19849:63"/>
               <head>THE SEVENTH DISCOVRSE VPON THE commotions that happened in <hi>Italie</hi> for the ſucceſſion of the Dutchies of <hi>Mantua</hi> and <hi>Montferrat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>TALIE enjoyed a profound peace, and fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it selfe wholly exempt from ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to diſturbe the repoſe of States, when on a ſudaine happened the death of <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> which (one may ſay) produced the ſeeds of all thoſe troubles that haue at ſeuerall times ſince diſreſted this Country. For, <hi>Charles Emanuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Sauoye,</hi> quarrelling (in right of his grand child <hi>Marie</hi>) for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Dutchie of <hi>Montferrat</hi> with <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> ſo inkindled the fire of warre in <hi>Italie</hi> as ſince it was neuer ſo well extinct, but that from time to time the cinders
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19849:64"/>
thereof haue cauſed new flames.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſupported rather by the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of his cauſe then by his owne forces, implored the aide of all the Prince, which by common intereſt were obliged not to ſuffer ſuch an outrage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> in whoſe hands at that time lay the gouernment of <hi>France,</hi> thinking of nothing more (during the minoritie of the King her ſonne) then to maintaine her ſelfe in peace, shee beleeued shee had enough to doe to smother the factions of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to appeaſe by all meanes thoſe that were capable to reſiſt her authoritie. So shee regarded the commotions of <hi>Italie</hi> no further then to endeauour to aſſwage them, and shee imployed her credit to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the <hi>Pope</hi> to interpoſe between the two parties for their accord.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> conſidered the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this diſcord after another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. For perceiuing the aduantage that might from thence accrue vnto him, he intermedled ſo farre in all the whole courſe of this affaire, as he failed but very little
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19849:64"/>
to draw from thence aduantages propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall to his deſignes.</p>
               <p>The Princes of <hi>Italie,</hi> whilſt the game was playing, looked on without medling therewith. The <hi>grand Duke</hi> vndertooke the defence of the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing he was obliged by his proper intereſt to aſſiſt the weaker againſt the ſtronger, beſides the particular reaſons that incited him thereunto.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> ſeeing the small aduancement that he could hope for from his entrepriſe, hearkened to an accord which was propoſed to him, and letting the buſineſſe be put to a treatie; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented himſelfe with the glorie that he durſt vndertake to vſurpe vpon his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſo all this goodly deſigne vanish'd it to ſmoake euen as it had beene plotted againſt all reaſon, it being not the intereſt of a Duke of <hi>Sauoye,</hi> now of any other Prince of <hi>Italie</hi> to imbroile himſelfe with his neighbours, ſince all the aduantage that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aid from their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is to ſee the difference reconciled by the power of one
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19849:65"/>
of theſe two Kings, which cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out manifeſt danger.</p>
               <p>This buſineſſe ſo ended, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> who had an eye euer vpon <hi>Piemont</hi> as a piece that lay fitt for him, ſaught a plauſible pretext to quarell the Duke of <hi>Sauoye.</hi> For, conſidering <hi>France</hi> out of caſe to medle with the affaires of <hi>Italie,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> by the late warre, exhaus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both of men and money, and the other Princes of <hi>Italie</hi> disunited betwixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, He thought fit to take this time to enter in to <hi>Piemont,</hi> hoping, as he had had the glorie to be arbitratour of the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, without gaining ſo fauourable an occaſion for his particular profitt, he would make amends for his default by reinflaming a ſecond warre. He inuaded then the Territories of the Duke of <hi>Sauoye,</hi> where finding more reſiſtance then he expected, he was in the end fayne to make peace. It is true that <hi>France</hi> beſtirred her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this ſecond occaſion, but the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall commendation therein is due to the Marshall <hi>de Leſdigui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et,</hi> who in all this
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19849:65"/>
warre (albeit that he followed his particular ends) engaged <hi>France</hi> to embrace her true intereſt, as shee ought to haue done in the former commotion.</p>
               <p>This ſecond trouble being appeaſed, the moſt vnderſtanding men judged well that <hi>Italie</hi> was not to continue long time in peace. Becauſe they ſaw <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> childleſſe, and his brother <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> leading ſo diſordered a life, as they beleeued he could not liue long, and the euent was answerable to their opinion. For, after <hi>Ferdinand's</hi> death, <hi>Vincent</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing the diſorders whereunto he had formerly accuſtomed his body) died, leau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his couſin <hi>Charles de Gonzague,</hi> Duke of <hi>Neuers</hi> heire of his Eſtates, who alone by all right could pretend there.</p>
               <p>The death of <hi>Vincent,</hi> although it was well enough foreſeene, yet it aſtonished all the Princes of <hi>Italie</hi> in ſuch a manner as euery one beganne ſeriously to conſider his affaires.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> foreſeeing that the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> could not endure the inheritance
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19849:66"/>
should be conferred on the Duke of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,</hi> and that therefore they would diuert the Emperour from giuing him the inueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they reſolued to doe their beſt for to fruſtrate their deſignes, ſuppoſing it would be a caſt too pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udiciall to them, to ſee a Prince depending on the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> eſtablished in an Eſtate ſet in the middeſt of their owne. That which moſt troubled the Republike, was the ſiege of <hi>Rochelle,</hi> where the King of <hi>France</hi> was ſo ingaged, that he had not any hope to be free a long time. The <hi>Pope</hi> was agitated with the ſame motiues as the Republicke of <hi>Venice,</hi> but he could not ſo openly shew vnto the King the deſire which he had to diſengage him from thence, leaſt he should thereby wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that his particular intereſt was more preualent then that of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> for the honour whereof they pleaded in depreſſing the <hi>Huguenots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other Princes of <hi>Italie</hi> kept cloſe, not daring to shew which way their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination was bent.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> onely imagined
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19849:66"/>
that he might profit by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s warre, and vpon the good opinion that he had of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, was perſwaded that he might share the conqueſt of <hi>Montferrat</hi> with the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king his aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the ſiege of <hi>Rochelle,</hi> and by the preſumption of the Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> thought fit to take his opportunitie to ſeiſe vpon <hi>Cazal.</hi> Wee muſt confeſſe that his deſigne was well conceiued, and with great likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lood of a fortunate ſucceſſe. Hitherto the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had in euery thing ſo well taken their time, that it ſeemed a thing impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to croſſe their deſignes, neuertheleſſe the wheele of their good fortunes beganne here to ſtop, and from hence forward wee haue ſeene a continuall company of ill accidents befall them, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h laſt euen to this day. For <hi>Loüys</hi> by an incredible diligence and reſolution takes <hi>Rochelle</hi> in deſpite of the <hi>English,</hi> forceth the Streight of <hi>Suze,</hi> relieueth <hi>Cazal,</hi> and ſo endangers the Dutchie of <hi>Milaine,</hi> that had it not beene for the troubles in <hi>Languedork</hi> which
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19849:67"/>
he deſired to make an end of, he might haue carried it away from the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> at the firſt blow.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſecure themſelues, and recouering the paths of their ordinarie pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſeiſe vpon the <hi>Griſons,</hi> cauſe moſt mightie Armies to paſſe that way, ſend Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> to the gouernment of <hi>Milaine,</hi> raiſe an armie in <hi>Italie,</hi> and beſiege <hi>Cazal</hi> anew.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewys</hi> ſendeth ſtrong forces into <hi>Piemont.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> would amuſe him with hopes of a peace: but he met with his match, with ſuch an vndaunted cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage that both in ſight of him and <hi>Spinola,</hi> he forced from him <hi>Pignerol,</hi> which will be an euerlaſting memoriall to poſteritie of the Raigne of <hi>Lewis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſiege of <hi>Cazal</hi> continues. The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence rageth in both the two armies. The <hi>Venetians</hi> receiue an ouerthrow towards the <hi>Mantuan.</hi> The citie of <hi>Mantua</hi> is ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed. Notwithſtanding all theſe accidents <hi>Lewis</hi> aſſembles new forces, and prouides to relieue <hi>Cazal,</hi> In the meane time he
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19849:67"/>
falles ſicke at <hi>Lyons.</hi> The <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſowes diſſention in his Counſell, which interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the courſe of ſo many heroïke actions, and after ſo many ſtormes paſt, one ſeemes vpon the point to ſuffer shipwracke in the hauen. There appeared his vertue againſt whom all theſe deuiſes were contriued, for at length he got out of this Labyrinth by the clue of honour. The King recouers his health: <hi>Cazal</hi> is brauely relieued: and the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> not onely reeſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in his Dominions, but (which will ſeeme incredible to after ages) he is inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted therein by the <hi>Emperour.</hi> The <hi>Grizons</hi> are ſet at libertie: <hi>Italie</hi> is freed from the armies of Strangers: the port lies open to her aſſiſtance, and for diuers defections of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> they make ſure of his Eſtates by which meanes the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Italie</hi> with <hi>Flanders</hi> in barred</p>
               <p>See here the true and liuely table of theſe differences, where note firſt of all the Duke of <hi>Sauoye</hi> his fault in hauing imagined that he should share <hi>Moniferrat</hi> with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> in deſpite of <hi>France,</hi> it being a
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19849:68"/>
caſe moſt euident, that he could not faile to be diſpoyled by the one or the other, or by both two together, if extraordinarie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence had not beene vſed towards him.</p>
               <p>It is alſo a thing wholly manifeſt that the Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> hath forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maxime of his true intereſt in taking by a fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of jollitie the partie of the <hi>Empe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our</hi> againſt that of <hi>France,</hi> in a ſeaſon when the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> was ſo vnable to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fend herſelfe, and that of <hi>France</hi> ſo free to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Emperour,</hi> he cannot excuſe himſelfe for hauing inuaded <hi>Italie</hi> before he was ſure of <hi>Germanie,</hi> and for hauing quitted the pretence of Religion (which hath ſo much ſerued him) in oppreſſing the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> being a great <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reſolution of <hi>France</hi> will be for euer memorable, which notwithſtanding the ſiege of <hi>Roehelle</hi> aſſiſted by the <hi>English:</hi> and the warre in <hi>Languedoc</hi> which the <hi>Spaniard</hi> made shew to foment, has not albeit euer abandonned her true maximes, in aſſiſting
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19849:68"/>
powerfully her Neigbours, and euery where dashing the projects of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Whence I conclude, that the glorie of the King, the greatneſſe of his State, and the eminent reputation that he now enjoyeth, will continue as long as he shall remaine conſtant in this reſolution.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
